<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good man a publick good, 1. passively, 2. actively. As it was manifested in a sermon preached to the Honourable House of Commons, at the late solemne fast: January 31. 1643. By Daniel Cavvdrey, minister of the Gospell at Great Billing in Northhamptonshire, and one of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
            <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E34_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859270</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 6:E34[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good man a publick good, 1. passively, 2. actively. As it was manifested in a sermon preached to the Honourable House of Commons, at the late solemne fast: January 31. 1643. By Daniel Cavvdrey, minister of the Gospell at Great Billing in Northhamptonshire, and one of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
                  <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Harper, for Charles Greene, and P.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643 [i.e. 1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "1. passively, 2. actively." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: :Feb. 23th:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXIX, 8 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111342:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GOOD MAN A PVBLICK GOOD,
<list>
                  <item>1. PASSIVELY,</item>
                  <item>2. ACTIVELY.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As it was Manifeſted in a Sermon preached to the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, at the late Solemne Faſt: <hi>January</hi> 31. 1643.</p>
            <p>By DANIEL CAVVDREY. Miniſter of the Goſpell at Great Billing in Northamptonſhire, and one of the Aſſembly of DIVINES.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. Cor. 12.15.</hi>
                  </bibl> I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you, though the more abundantly I love you, the leſſe I am loved.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 10.11.12.</hi>
                  </bibl> The Good Shepheard giveth his life for the Sheepe: But he that is an hireling and not the Shepheard, whoſe owne the Sheepe are not, ſeeth the wolfe comming, and leaves the Sheep, and fleeth becauſe he is an hireling, and careth not for the Sheep.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Tho. Harper,</hi> for <hi>Charles Greene,</hi> and <hi>P. W.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111342:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111342:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Honourable Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourable, and ever-Honoured Patriots:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis poor and plain Sermon, as it was firſt preached in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to your Command, and heard with a great deale of Religious Attention; ſo it is now moſt humbly preſented to your hands and eyes. Wherein the Preachers aime and intention was not,<note place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i monet ut f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od j m ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci, &amp;c.</note> either to informe your Judgements in what you knew not, or to perſwade your Obedience to what you did not, but to encourage and comfort you, in what you already did, even ſpend your ſelves in the Publicke Good. The which he conceived the rather to be moſt neceſſary for him to doe: Firſt, becauſe of the great difficulty of the worke you are ingaged in, by reaſon of thoſe <hi>Scornfull men,</hi> who have brought the City into a <hi>ſnare,</hi> or rather ſet the Kingdome on <hi>fire.</hi> Secondly, becauſe of thoſe great diſcouragements which you have long wraſtled with, through the frowardneſſe and unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the people of this land, who have withdrawne (many of them) their aſſiſtance, and ſtopped up thoſe wels that ſhould afford you wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to quench that fire. And had not the Lord himſelf ſtood by you, and endued you with Wiſdome, Goodneſſe, Meekneſſe, the wickedneſſe of the one ſort, and the perverſeneſſe of the other ſort, might have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your hands to faint, and your hearts to faile in the proſecution of the Worke. But bleſſed be God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who both raiſed you up unto us, and raiſed and kept up your ſpirits, to be conſtant and active, for ſuch a time as this: But it is uſuall with God ſo to doe. As it is obſervable in Nature (Phyſitians ſay) that as there are Nationall diſeaſes, ſo there are peculiar Nationall remedies: So commonly in the greateſt diſtreſſes of his Church, and greateſt oppoſition of Malignants, God
<pb facs="tcp:111342:3"/> is pleaſed to raiſe up defendants proportionable to theſe neceſſities. This is evident in many paſſages of the ſacred Story; eſpecially in the booke of Judges, in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> and <hi>Eſthers</hi> time. The two parties in the Text, are not ſo much oppoſed one againſt another, viz. <hi>Scornfull men,</hi> and <hi>Wiſe men,</hi> as they are in the preſent experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of theſe times. Never did any Kingdome know and finde ſo great a generation of <hi>Scornfull men,</hi> not onely the lower ranke of meane Malignants, who have ſcorned and ſcoffed at Religion and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſo long till they have ſcoffed themſelves out of all, even <hi>ſhewes</hi> of Religion, and into unbeleefe of all relations of ſucceſſes, as falſe and fabulous: but even thoſe of the ſecond and third magnitudes, who like <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballat,</hi> have jeered and derided all your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, as weake and worthleſſe: ſaying as they, <hi>What do theſe feeble men? will they fortifie themſelves? will they make an end in a day?</hi> Will they pull downe the Old, and ſet up a new Church in a day? Nay, have they not flouted your faſtings and prayings, upon the leaſt ſucceſſes of their party? and ſome of them ſaid where is now your God? But againe I ſay, Bleſſed be God (who reſiſts the proud, and gives grace to the Humble) that hath as it were, created a generation of <hi>Wiſe men,</hi> in a way of oppoſition to thoſe <hi>Scornfull men,</hi> to breake thoſe ſnares, and quench thoſe fires which they have kindled. Wherein God hath not only magnified his owne Wiſdome and Goodneſſe, in providing and fitting the Remedy to the Diſeaſe; but alſo manifeſted to all the world, your <hi>Wiſdome</hi> in diſcovering their <hi>ſnares,</hi> and your <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in quenching their fires. Truly <hi>(worthy Patriots)</hi> next under God, we cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that the Kingdome, the whole Iſland, is beholding to you for its preſent preſervation. And though you have met with an unthankefull generation for the preſent, yet we doubt not, but the children yet unborne, ſhall have cauſe to call you Bleſſed; as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers of our breaches, as the reſtorers of paths to dwell in, and above all, as the bleſſed Reformers of Church and State. Which that you may be, ſhall be the dayly prayer, of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humbly devoted Servant in the Lord, DANIEL CAVVDREY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111342:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON <hi>Preached before</hi> The honourable Houſe of COMMONS, at the publike Faſt, <hi>Ian.</hi> 31. 1643.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Proverbs, 29.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Scornefull men bring a City into a ſnare, but wiſe men turne away wrath.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Booke of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Proverbs in three things.</note> as it hath the common <hi>Honour,</hi> with other ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to be called <hi>Canonicall;</hi> ſo it hath ſome ſpeciall <hi>Prerogatives</hi> above the reſt, and that in a threefold reſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the <hi>Excellence</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. The Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies.</note> and preheminence of the <hi>Sentences</hi> therein contained; being, for the moſt part, received principles or <hi>Canons</hi> of wiſedome, acknowledged generally by all, eſpecially by the wiſe. And for this cauſe they are called <hi>Proverbs.</hi> Look what <hi>Maximes</hi> are in Law, <hi>Axioms</hi> in Logick, <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> in Phyſick, <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegmes</hi> in hiſtorie or morality, ſuch are theſe <hi>Proverbs</hi> in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity: the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the original, carries their <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> in the very forehead. It comes from a roote that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to <hi>Rule,</hi> as a Lord or Prince. They are <hi>principes,</hi> or <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pales ſententiae,</hi> princely or principall ſentences, not onely
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111342:4"/> from their Authour King <hi>Salomon,</hi> chap. 1. 1. but alſo from their <hi>worth</hi> &amp; <hi>authority,</hi> being, as I may ſo ſay, <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders</hi> of our Aſſent and Judgement, for their Authenticall and acknowledged veritie: that's the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In their <hi>Independance</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce.</note> uſually one upon another; every verſe almoſt, yea every <hi>Homiſtichium,</hi> or halfe verſe, being a compleat <hi>Doctrine</hi> of it ſelfe, as <hi>Proverbs</hi> commonly are ſhort, and full. In other Scriptures, a man muſt read many verſes, ſometimes at leaſt, before he can make up the ſenſe, or profitable inſtructions therein contained: but here he hath in two or three words, a full propoſition, or Doctrine expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his view. In which reſpect, they may be compared, not ſo fitly to a <hi>Chaine</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> where each piece is linked to, and drawes on its fellow; as to a <hi>Chaine</hi> of precious <hi>Pearles,</hi> all put upon one ſtring, having indeed, a kind of <hi>Contaction,</hi> (as I may ſay) but no neceſſary <hi>Connexion,</hi> or <hi>Cohaerence,</hi> one upon another. And that's the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the mutuall <hi>Illumination,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Their Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> or Illuſtration one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Somtimes by way of ſhort <hi>Compariſon,</hi> by way of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, or Diſſimilitude, in which reſpect every thing is (as they ſay) twiſe underſtood, though but once ſpoken, ſomtimes by way of <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> and contraries, we ſay, ſet one againſt another, do illuſtrate, and enlighten one another; As light and darkeneſſe in nature, white and blacke in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, do make each other more notable or notorious: The verſes, or halfe verſes ſometimes, being like unto two <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,</hi> or torches, lighted and ſet up, which are ſeene, both by their owne, and by each others light. And that's the third.</p>
            <p>All theſe are obſervable, and applyable to this preſent verſe, and text of ours:<note place="margin">2. Applyable to the text.</note> Firſt, it containes two Ancient and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed principles of wiſedome, ſo full and cleere, that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men, have been able to ſee them; The one is this, <hi>That an ill man is an ill neighbour,</hi> acknowledged by a Heathen Poet, who ſaid long agoe, <hi>The whole City, fares the worſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heſiod.</note> 
               <hi>for one wicked man:</hi> He may ſeeme to have borrowed it from our <hi>Salomon,</hi> in our text. <hi>Scornefull men, bring a City into a ſnare, or ſet a whole City on fire:</hi> The other is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111342:4"/> this, <hi>That a good man is a common good:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo ſaid one of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens wiſe men; whoſe candle <hi>Solomon</hi> ſeems to have ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our Text when he ſaid in oppoſition to the former, <hi>wiſe men turn away wrath.</hi> Secondly, they are two propoſitions, but independents, ſhining with their own native light: And yet thirdly, though they doe not need to borrow, yet they doe eaſily and willingly lend and affoord their aſſiſtance to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate one another, as we ſhall the better ſee, if we take them, and conſider them aſunder by way of explication.<note place="margin">3. The expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the words.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, what is here meant by <hi>ſcornefull men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Scornfull men, what.</note> The words in the originall are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>viri irriſionis,</hi> men of ſcorne; not paſſively, as <hi>ſcorned,</hi> but actively as ſcorners, or <hi>ſcorning.</hi> The words are very emphaticall, and with the Hebrewes (who know no degrees of compariſon) carry the force of the ſuperlative degree. The like phraſe is uſed four times in this very Chapter; as <hi>a man of reproofes,</hi> ver. 1. that is, a man very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reproved: <hi>a man of oblations</hi> or gifts, ver. 4. that is, a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious briber; men of blouds, verſ. 10. that is, as we read it, bloud-thirſty men, men ſoakt in bloud, cruell bloudy men. And once more, <hi>a man of anger,</hi> verſ. 22. that is, a moſt haſty and cholericke man. So here, <hi>men of ſcorne,</hi> is more then ſcorners, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1. (who yet, are there made the worſt and higheſt degree of ſinners, <hi>ungodly, ſinners, ſcorners</hi>) for it implies the worſt of ſcorners, and the higheſt degree of wickedneſſe. Not ſecret ſcorners as <hi>Mical</hi> was at firſt, who deſpiſed <hi>David</hi> in her heart; but open ſcorners, profeſſed and proud ſcorners, that deride not only good men, and goodneſſe, but the Meſſengers and Miniſters of God (and in them, God himſelf) in their admonitions, reproofes or threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings (as thoſe did, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16.) being neare of kin to that man ſpoken of, verſ. 1. A man of <hi>reproofes,</hi> or often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, yet ſcorning all, and hardening his heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what is meant by thoſe words, <hi>Bring into a ſnare:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Bring into a ſnare.</note> The word in the originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is diverſly rendered by Interpreters, as they ſuppoſe the root of it to be different. Some derive it from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies a ſnare: Now a <hi>ſnare</hi> in Scripture ſignifies ſometimes perplexities, or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111342:5"/> perplexing troubles. <hi>The ungodly is ſnared in the workes of his owne hands, Pſal.</hi> 9.16. Sometimes ſome fearfull judgement of God. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ungodly he ſhall raine ſnares, fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ſtorme and tempeſt, this ſhall be the portion of their cup, Pſal.</hi> 11.6. According to this ſenſe of the word, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that <hi>ſcornfull</hi> men do bring perplexities and troubles upon a place, and provoke God (by ſcorning reproofes &amp;c.) to bring moſt fearfull judgements upon it. Some againe derive it from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to blow or puffe at: as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.5. <hi>I will ſet him at reſt from him that puffes at him:</hi> for ſo ſcornfull men uſe to expreſſe their ſcorne; or rather to blow at a coale, and ſo to ſet all on fire:<note place="margin">Or ſet on fire.</note> Scornfull men are <hi>flabella Diaboli</hi> the Divells <hi>bellows</hi> to blow the coals of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtrife and contention till they ſet the City on fire, and ſo our margine expreſſes it; or to blow the coales of Gods wrath and fury, till he by his judgements (compared alſo to fire in Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. laſt) ſet all on a flame. The ſumme is, <hi>Scornfull men are miſchievous inſtruments,</hi> both ſtirring up ſeditions and contentions amongſt the people, and ſo enſnaring them with perplexities (as <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver-ſmith did at <hi>Epheſus Acts</hi> 19.) and alſo incenſing the wrath of God againſt them, and ſo <hi>enfiring</hi> them with moſt fearfull judgements.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, what is here meant by the <hi>City,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. City what.</note> the word is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken either <hi>Metonymically,</hi> the ſubject for the adjunct, the City, for the Inhabitants of the City; or <hi>Synechdochically,</hi> the ſpeciall for the generall; the City, that is, any place where thoſe ſcornefull men live, the Houſe, the Towne, the City, the Countrey, the Kingdome. Their miſchiefe extends not to themſelves alone, but to all about them; they are the <hi>common peſtilences,</hi> and <hi>publicke enemies</hi> in the places where they live.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, what is here to be underſtood by <hi>wiſe men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Wiſe men, who.</note> the word is good, and of great eſteem. But perhaps ſome may queſtion <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſdome in the choice thereof, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an oppoſition to the former part (as the particle, <hi>But,</hi> implies) it may be demanded, how are <hi>wiſe men</hi> oppoſed to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111342:5"/> 
               <hi>ſcornfull men.</hi> It ſeems more congruous, he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Meeke or humble men turne away wrath;</hi> ſo the oppoſition had been fairer and clearer; or elſe, in the former part hee ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Fooliſh men bring a City into a ſnare,</hi> as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſed to <hi>Wiſe men.</hi> True, but there is the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret <hi>wiſdome</hi> in this oppoſition, that the Spirit of God inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded we ſhould take notice of: For it intimates unto us two things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That <hi>ſcornfull</hi> and proud men, how ever they may thinke themſelves <hi>wiſe,</hi> are indeed but fooles in Wiſdomes account; and in our common ſpeech we ſo ſtile them, when we ſay of a man of a ſcornfull carriage, he is a <hi>proud foole:</hi> Yea, in the language of the Scripture, all wicked men, (of which, ſcornfull men are chiefeſt, as we ſaid afore) are fools and ſimple: Therefore as ſometimes a ſcorner and a wicked man are <hi>Synonymas</hi> in Scripture, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.7. <hi>[He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth a ſcorner, getteth to himſelfe ſhame, and he that rebuketh a wicked man, getteth himſelfe a blot.]</hi> He that in the firſt part is called a <hi>ſcorner,</hi> in the ſecond part is called a <hi>wicked man,</hi> implying them to be convertible, every ſcorner is a wicked man; and every wicked man is a ſcorner: ſo a <hi>wicked man</hi> and a <hi>foole,</hi> are alſo one with the Spirit of God. <hi>Solomons</hi> fool (ſo often mentioned in this Booke, and elſewhere) is no better, no other then a <hi>wicked man:</hi> And that is the firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That <hi>wiſe men</hi> are <hi>meeke</hi> and <hi>humble men,</hi> and only meeke and humble men are wiſe: This the Spirit of God would have us to take notice of, by oppoſing <hi>wiſe men</hi> to proud and ſcornfull men. Therefore, it is worth obſerving alſo, that as proud men, and ſcornfull men, are parallels in Scripture, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Proud and haughty ſcorner is his name who dealeth in proud wrath:</hi> and ſometimes we heare, <hi>The proud have laid a ſnare for me,</hi> as here the ſcornfull; ſo <hi>wiſe men,</hi> and <hi>meeke men,</hi> are very neare a kin, or rather one and the ſame. So Saint <hi>James</hi> would have us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, when he ſayes, [<hi>Who is a wiſe man and endued with knowledge amongſt you? let him ſhew out of a good converſation his workes with meekneſſe of wiſdome, Jam.</hi> 3.13.] And againe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111342:6"/> verſ. 17. <hi>[The wiſdome which is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, &amp;c.]</hi> By wiſe men therefore here, <hi>Solomon</hi> meanes <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> men, in ſpeciall and generally all Good men, who are only wiſe; his wiſe man is the ſame with a <hi>good man,</hi> as his <hi>foole</hi> with a <hi>wicked man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, what is here meant by <hi>wrath;</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Wrath, what, and what to turn it away.</note> by <hi>wrath</hi> ſome underſtand the anger of men, as of a King, <hi>Whoſe wrath is as the roaring of a Lion,</hi> and he is a wiſe man that knowes how to allay it; or of a tumultuous and enraged <hi>multitude</hi> ſet on fire by <hi>ſcornfull men.</hi> Others underſtand it of the <hi>wrath</hi> of God, which wicked ſcorners have incenſed, but onely wiſe men and good men know how to quench it. So that here is the cauſe put for the effects; the wrath of God for thoſe ſnares and perplexities, thoſe <hi>fires</hi> and judgements in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on a people by the wrath of God. And there is a great deale of wiſdome in the choiſe of this word, for it implies three things very conſiderable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>prevention</hi> of judgements<note place="margin">1. Prevention of judgements</note> ready to fall upon a people (by the wickedneſſe of ſcornefull men) by taking away, or turning away wrath, the cauſe thereof. So <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.1. <hi>A ſoft anſwer pacifies wrath;</hi> the wrath of God or men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>removall</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Removall.</note> of thoſe judgements which are inflicted, when a City is enſnared or enfired, <hi>wiſe men,</hi> good men, are ſo prevalent with God, that they help to break thoſe ſnares, and quench thoſe fires, by turning away the wrath of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>procuring</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Procuring bleſſings.</note> of mercies and bleſſings upon the place, for here is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as they call it, leſſe is ſaid, but more is underſtood as the oppoſition doth fairly ſuggeſt: <hi>Scornfull men bring a City into a ſnare, or ſet a City on fire:</hi> That is, they deprive a Land of mercies and bleſſings firſt, and then helpe to bring on judgements: So <hi>wiſe men</hi> doe not only prevent and remove judgements, but procure bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings on the places where they live, the Houſe, the Towne, the City, the Countrey, the Kingdome; which muſt the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be obſerved becauſe in this latter part, the City is not mentioned but underſtood, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the rule of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111342:6"/> So the ſumme of all will be this, <hi>That wiſe men are common and publick Goods to the places where they live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words thus explained, will yeeld us many good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations,<note place="margin">4. The obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations ſome.</note> we ſhall name ſome, but inſiſt chiefly upon one.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That all ſcornfull men (as all wicked men, whereof theſe are the worſt) how ever they thinke of themſelves, or others of them, are no wiſer then they ſhould be: that is, are no better, no other then fooles in wiſdomes account.</hi> It ariſes from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of <hi>ſcornfull</hi> men and <hi>wiſe</hi> men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That only meek and humble men (as all good men) how ever the world accounts them ſimple, are truly wiſe.</hi> It ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alſo from the oppoſition of <hi>wiſe</hi> men, and <hi>ſcornfull</hi> men, who are ever proud men, for ſcorne ariſes from pride, as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility from wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That ſcornfull men (the worſt of men) are publicke evills and miſchiefes to the places where they live:</hi> And that two wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Paſſively,</hi> as meriting and procuring the wrath and judgements of God upon theſe places.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Actively,</hi> as ſtudying, plotting and endeavouring miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes to the places: <hi>They bring a City into a ſnare, and ſet a City on fire.</hi> In the firſt ſenſe they are <hi>flagella Dei:</hi> In the ſecond, <hi>flabella Diaboli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>That on the contrary, wiſe men (that is good men, for they are</hi> Synonyma's <hi>in Scripture) are publick Goods to the places where they live:</hi> And that alſo two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Paſſively,</hi> the places being bleſſed for their ſakes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Actively,</hi> as ſeeking, ſtudying, endeavouring the publick Good, being men of publick ſpirits, preferring the publick Good, before their owne private intereſts.</p>
            <p>But to handle all theſe particulars, as it is a little imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent (ſome of them being only hinted, and not directly here intended) ſo it is as much impoſſible, conſidering that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time which is allowed me. I ſhall therefore draw out only the laſt generall concluſion, conſiſting of two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular branches, taking ſometimes notice of the oppoſite part, and the other conſiderations, for illuſtration, confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111342:7"/> or application, as ſhall be moſt expedient.</p>
            <p>The generall Obſervation is this; <hi>Good men are publick Goods</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, Good men publicke goods.</note> 
               <hi>to the places where they live.</hi> That this is rightly collected, is evident to an obſerving eye by the former explication: This we ſhall endeavour to make good in both the branches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore propounded, both <hi>paſſively</hi> as God bleſſes the places for their ſakes; and alſo <hi>actively,</hi> as they are men of <hi>publicke ſpirits,</hi> ſeeking principally the good of the Community.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Good men are publicke goods paſſively;</hi> God for their ſakes bleſſing the Places,<note place="margin">1. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſively, as bleſſings to the places.</note> Family, Towne, City, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Kingdome where they live. This is thus made good.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are <hi>promiſes</hi> made unto them for this very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,<note place="margin">1. This is promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> as to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 12.2.3. <hi>I will bleſſe thee, and make thy name great, and thou ſhalt be a bleſſing. And I will bleſſe them that bleſſe thee, and curſe them that curſe thee, and in thee ſhall all families of the earth bee bleſſed.</hi> To this may bee added that other conditionall promiſe to the ſame <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 18.26. <hi>If I finde in Sodome fifty righteous within the City, then I will ſpare all the place for their ſakes.</hi> Nay a lower condiſcenſion we finde there: <hi>I will not deſtroy it for tennes ſake.</hi> The ſame promiſe is made to <hi>Iob</hi> upon ſuppoſition of his repentance and turning to God. <hi>The innocent ſhall deliver the Iſland, and it is delivered by the pureneſſe of thine hands, Iob</hi> 22.30. The like or a yet lower condiſcenſion we finde, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Runne ye too and fro through the ſtreets of Ieruſalem, and ſee, and know, and ſeek in the broad places thereof, if ye can finde a man, (one man) if there be any that executeth iudgement and ſeeketh the truth, and I will pardon it.</hi> Adde but one more, and that is, <hi>Ezek</hi> 22.30. <hi>I ſought for a man (but one man) among them that ſhould make up the hedge, and ſtand in the gap before me for the land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it, but I found none, therefore have I powred out mine indignation upon them, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. This is performed.</note> We finde the performances of this promiſe in many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. This was made good to <hi>Abraham</hi> in the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Nephew <hi>Lot</hi> and his family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.29. <hi>God remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred</hi> Abraham (that is, his prayer and pleading with God that he would not deſtroy the righteous with the wicked,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111342:7"/> Chap. 18.) <hi>and ſent</hi> Lot <hi>out of the midſt of the overthrow.</hi> Nay <hi>Lot</hi> himſelfe had experience of this grace and favour, that as he preſerved <hi>Zoar,</hi> ſo the City of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and the reſt could not be deſtroyed ſo long as he was in it: See but the power he had with God: For the firſt, <hi>Lot</hi> did not directly petition for the ſparing of that little City <hi>Zoar,</hi> but for his owne ſafety, yet God is pleaſed to ſpare it for his ſake: Thus he ſayes, <hi>See I have accepted thee concerning this, that I will not overthrow this City, for which thou haſt ſpoken.</hi> For the ſecond,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.21.22.</note> thus more ſtrangely, <hi>Haſte thee, eſcape thither, for I cannot doe any thing till thou come thither.</hi> Not only while <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodome</hi> was it ſpared for his ſake, but all the while he was going to <hi>Zoar,</hi> it was not deſtroyed. The Iſraelites had manifold experiences in this kind, in the wilderneſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they provoked God forty yeares: <hi>Therefore he ſaid that he would deſtroy them, had not</hi> Moſes <hi>his choſen ſtood before him in the breach, to turne away his wrath</hi> (the words of our Text) <hi>leſt he ſhould deſtroy them, Pſal.</hi> 106.23. And ſo verſe 29.30. <hi>Thus they provoked him to anger with their inventions, and the plague brake in upon them: Then ſtood up</hi> Phineas <hi>and executed judgement, and ſo the plague was ſtayed.</hi> Theſe were examples of favour for prevention, or removall of judgements: Take ſome for procuring of Good: <hi>God bleſſed the Egyptians houſe for</hi> Joſephs <hi>ſake, Gen.</hi> 39.5. <hi>And the bleſſing of the Lord was upon all that he had, in the houſe and in the field.</hi> And what a bleſſing he was to the whole land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> for a bleſſing of plenty for ſeven yeares together, is to be ſeen, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.47. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo was thus highly honoured, that he ſaved the lives of all that ſailed with him in the ſhip, two hundred threeſcore and fifteen ſoules beſide himſelfe, <hi>Acts</hi> 27.24 <hi>Lo,</hi> ſayes the Angell, <hi>God hath given thee all them that ſaile with thee.</hi> Inſomuch, that he confidently tells them. <hi>There ſhall be no l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe of any mans life among you, but of the Shippe,</hi> verſe 22.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This was ever a knowne and confeſſed truth;<note place="margin">3. This is confeſſed by all.</note> both good and bad men have taken it for granted, That they ſhall fare the better for Good peoples ſake. Hence it was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111342:8"/> that <hi>Bara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (a good, but a weake man) deſired <hi>Deborah</hi> an holy Propheteſſe, to goe with him to the warre, yea profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed he would not goe without her, <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.8. as placing both his ſafety and victory in her preſence. And wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> ſolicites <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> to goe to warre with him, as hoping to proſper the better for his ſake. In a word, for this reaſon wicked men have ſo often deſired the prayers of righteous men, as diſtruſting themſelves, and truſting more to finde mercy for their ſakes, then their owne.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſame is further confirmed by grounds of reaſon:<note place="margin">4. This is grounded on Reaſons.</note> Firſt, Good men, or Righteous men, are Gods <hi>Favourites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Good men are Gods Favourites.</note> ſo they are called in the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>Saints</hi> we ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, the word ſignifies, his <hi>Favourites,</hi> from the root <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies Mercy, and Favour; ſo his Saints are ſuch as actually are mercifull, <hi>The Good man is mercifull and len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth;</hi> but eſpecially <hi>paſſively</hi> as received to the <hi>mercy</hi> or <hi>favour</hi> of God, (as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed in Greeke, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>Lu.</hi> 1.28. that is, <hi>graced</hi> with God, or highly <hi>favoured</hi> of God) They are Gods <hi>Favourites,</hi> I ſay, and therefore for their ſakes much Good is done to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have any relation to them. Conſider but what <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaies to <hi>Iob,</hi> perſwading him to humble himſelfe, and be acquainted with God, <hi>Iob</hi> 22.21. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to turne unto him; he uſes amongſt others, this argument, verſ. 27. <hi>Thou ſhalt make thy prayer unto him, &amp; he ſhal hear thee, and thou ſhalt pay thy vows. Thou ſhalt alſo decree a thing and it ſhall be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed unto thee,</hi> ver. 28. And laſt of all, (as before) <hi>The Iſland ſhall be delivered by the pureneſſe of thy hands,</hi> verſ. 30. Such grace and favour ſhalt thou finde with God. It is very obſervable that the Pſalmiſt hath delivered, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.7.8. <hi>The Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuteth judgement for the oppreſſed, he giveth food to the hungry, the Lord looſeth the priſoners, the Lord openeth the eyes of the blinde, the Lord raiſeth them that are bowed downe.</hi> Theſe are all common mercies to wicked men: but what will he doe for righteous men? Sure much more for them; yet marke what he addes inſtead of all: <hi>The Lord loveth the righteous:</hi> as if his love were better then all thoſe before named, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111342:8"/> rather becauſe his love is the ground of all other favours, and becauſe he loves them, he can deny them nothing for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or others. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.12. <hi>The Lord bleſſeth the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; the Lord heareth the prayers of the righteous, &amp;c.</hi> Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that when God is reſolved to puniſh a People or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he is faine to bid his <hi>Favourites</hi> not to pray for them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 14. and 15. Chap. Pray not for this people: Nay to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them, not to intreat him, but to let him alone, that hee may deſtroy them, as he did to <hi>Moſes.</hi> It is a very extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary caſe when ſuch <hi>Favourites</hi> as <hi>Noah, Iob</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> cannot deliver a Nation, but only their owne ſoules, <hi>Eze.</hi> 14.14. any ordinary favour they may procure for others, as well as for themſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, all <hi>Good</hi> things, as they are <hi>promiſed</hi> to,<note place="margin">2. All good things are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for them.</note> ſo they are primarily, if not only <hi>intended</hi> for the <hi>Good;</hi> nothing for wicked men, but as by reaſon of their vicinity, and neare neighbourhood they fall upon them, becauſe they cannot well be ſeparated. <hi>All is yours,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle to his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian</hi> Saints, the <hi>world</hi> it ſelfe is yours, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. laſt. Our Saviour hath made a diſtribution of the whole world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. Heaven is given to the poore in ſpirit. Earth is bequeathed to the meeke: what then remaines for the proud and ſcornfull wicked men, but Hell, their proper inheritance? as it is ſaid of <hi>Judas,</hi> that ſonne or heire of perdition, that he was gone to his owne place, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.25. Now then, if wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men have any thing, they have it for the godly mens ſakes, becauſe they are mixt together. As the Sunne ſhines upon the ſtony rocks, as well as upon the low valleyes; and the raine falls upon the barren mountaines, as well as upon the fruitfull medowes, but were intended only for the latter. The tares in the field receive and pertake of the dewes and ſhoures of heaven, but not for their owne, but for the corns ſake. The Heathen man ſaw this truth by the twilight of nature; <hi>God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>provided all Good things for the Good, but they befall the evill men, becauſe they cannot be ſeparated. And it is better to profit or doe good to evill men for the Goods ſake, then to bee wanting to the Good for evill mens ſake.</hi> The world it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111342:9"/> ſelfe ſtands for the Elects ſake; if their number were once made up, as the old world periſhed by water ſo ſoone as <hi>Noah</hi> and his family were houſed in the Arke, ſo this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world ſhould be deſtroyed with fire, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. All judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men.</note>Thirdly, as all Good things are intended for the Good: ſo all judgements and puniſhments, are provided and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the <hi>wicked,</hi> none for Good men, further then they communicate more or leſſe, in the wickedneſſe of the places and times where they live. <hi>The whip is for the Aſſe, and the rod for the fooles backe, Prov.</hi> 26.3. <hi>Great plagues remaine for the ungodly, Pſal.</hi> 32.10. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ungodly he ſhall raine ſnares, ſtorme, and tempeſt, fire and brimſtone, Pſal,</hi> 11. Now then, becauſe it is againſt juſtice to puniſh the Righteous with the wicked, or for wicked mens ſake, <hi>Abraham</hi> pleads it ſo with God, <hi>Wilt thou deſtroy the righteous with the wicked? farre be that from thee; Shall not the Judge of all the earth doe right, Gen.</hi> 18 25. And God admits the plea as juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as you may ſee, <hi>If I finde fifty righteous, I will ſpare all the place for their ſakes.</hi> Either therefore God muſt <hi>ſeparate</hi> the righteous from the wicked (as ſometimes indeed hee does) or elſe he muſt <hi>deſtroy</hi> the righteous with the wicked, or for the wickeds ſake, which is unjuſt; or elſe hee muſt <hi>ſpare</hi> the wicked for the righteous ſake. And we have a kinde of a Proverbe common amongſt us, It is better to ſave two Nocents, then to deſtroy one Innocent. The very tares (as was ſaid) are ſpared for the wheats ſake.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Good men are ſtudious and active for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Good,<note place="margin">4. They are active for the publick Good</note> (as we ſhall heare anon) as well as for their owne, yea above, and with neglect of their owne Good. They imploy all their parts, wiſdome, ſtrength, riches, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, for the Publicke Good; all their prayers and power with God to the Good of others. Now it is a wonderfull wel-pleaſing thing to God to ſee men of his owne diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to neglect themſelves for Gods glory and his peoples Good, that he will, even for their ſakes, ſtay or remove a judgement, and drop downe bleſſings upon others, and they perhaps wicked. As when <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired to be blotted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111342:9"/> out of Gods Booke, rather then Gods glory ſhould ſuffer, or his people be deſtroyed; God takes it ſo well, that he ſpares a rebellious people for his ſake. Theſe reaſons may ſerve for the confirmation:<note place="margin">5. The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then.</note> We now come to the application of it, before we proceed to the next.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then on the contrary; wicked evill men,<note place="margin">1. Wicked men are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick evills.</note> are publicke evills; they are not hurtfull onely to themſelves, that is the leaſt part of their Illneſſe, but to the Places, Families, Townes, Cities, Countries, the whole Iſland or Kingdome where they live. <hi>One ſinner deſtroyeth much good. Eccleſ.</hi> 9. laſt. and hinders much good, and brings much evill; brings an houſe, or City into a <hi>Snare,</hi> or ſets them all on fire. One ſpark hath been the cauſe of the burning of a whole town: One <hi>Achan</hi> troubled and had like to have ruined a whole Armie. One and every wicked man is a curſe, a peſt, a viper to the place where he lives. <hi>A fruitfull land, he maketh barren for the wickedneſſe of them that dwell therein. Pſal.</hi> 107.34. Theſe, theſe are the men that violate the peace and happineſſe of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that with-hold Good things from it: The Prophet <hi>Zach.</hi> 5. ſaw in a viſion a flying rowle, written full of curſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and within: <hi>And it ſhall enter (ſayes the Lord) into the houſe of the theefe, and of him that ſweareth falſely, &amp;c.</hi> It is a wonder to me, that many families and townes, are not ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd and deſtroyed, for the wickedneſſe of them that dwell therein, ſo full of curſes, and oathes, and blaſphemies. No wonder there is ſo much trouble and perplexity in our Cities and Countries, and whole Kingdome, ſeeing wickedneſſe ſo much abounds n every place: But eſpecially conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that our land is ſo full of <hi>ſcornefull men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſpecially ſcornefull men.</note> both ſecret and open. Secret ſcorners, that in their hearts, deride and deſpiſe, not onely Goodmen, but Goodneſſe it ſelfe, and the power and practiſe of Godlineſſe. Many perhaps, that make a faire ſhew of Religion, frequent the Aſſemblies, obſerve Faſts and daies of Humiliation, and yet in their hearts deſpiſe and deride all ſuch Devotions, as either needleſſe, or uſeleſſe. Many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſcorners, that are profeſſed mockers and flouters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and them that deſire to profeſſe it, in the ſtricteſt and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111342:10"/> exacteſt way. Hypocriticall Mockers at Feaſts, as <hi>Dauid</hi> calls them, the drunkards that made ſongs of him, and all that profeſſe Godlineſſe. Amongſt theſe you may reckon your <hi>Stage-players,</hi> who had skoffed Religion, out of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance with many. <hi>You have done well, to put them downe, and ſhall do better if you keepe them downe.</hi> Adde to theſe, your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane ſouldiers, who undertaking to fight for Religion, do as much ſcorne it and the profeſſors of it, with names of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, as any of the Cavaliers. Can we wonder to ſee our Cities and Countries ſo enſnared, and enfired; when all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are full of ſuch skorners, as our text mentions? <hi>When one bleſſes and another curſes, which will God heare?</hi> ſayd a Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. This mixture of ſo many ſcorners with ſome few wiſe men, in our Cities, in our Armies, makes things thus to hang in <hi>aequilibrio:</hi> Now we have a victory, then by and by a loſſe and defeat: God himſelfe ſeemes to be doubtfull whether he ſhould ſave us for ſome Good mens ſake, or deſtroy us for theſe many ſcorners ſake. <hi>Salvian</hi> complained of his times, and it is our caſe at this time. <hi>Si quis ex Nobilibus, &amp;c. If any of the Nobility or Gentry begin to be Religious, he preſently looſes the Honour of his Nobility: Oh (ſayes hee) what honour is there among Chriſtian people, when Religion makes men vile?</hi> Oh ſhamefull and unſufferable wickedneſſe! It is not ſo with any Religion as it is with ours. In any Religion of Jews, Turkes, Papiſts, the more ſtrict and exact, the more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and eſteemed: Only in the Proteſtant Religion, the ſtricter and preciſer, the more ſcorned and deſpiſed. It was a very noble act, that of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> Dan. 3.29. <hi>I make a decree, that every people, nation and language which ſpeake any thing amiſſe againſt the God of</hi> Shadrach, Meſhach, <hi>and</hi> Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nego, <hi>ſhall be cut in pieces, and their houſes ſhall be made a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, &amp;c.</hi> I could wiſh, that our Law-makers, would provide a Statute, that it might be lawful for no man, with impunity, to deride and ſcorne Religion, or the ſtrict profeſſion of it: And there is good reaſon for it; For 1. <hi>Scornefull men bring a City into a ſnare,</hi> or ſet a City on fire. 2. Their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be exemplary to others: <hi>Smite a Scorner and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111342:10"/> ſimple will beware.</hi> Prov. 19.25. <hi>When the ſcorner is puniſhed, the ſimple is made wiſe. Prov.</hi> 21.11. And once more (as if it were a matter of great obſervance, and greater conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence:) <hi>Caſt out the ſcorner, and contention ſhall goe out; yea ſtrife and reproach ſhall ceaſe. Prov.</hi> 22.10. Thirdly, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Though every Good man be a publicke Good and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the place, yet eſpecially the <hi>heires of reſtraint,</hi> (as a Magiſtrate is deſcribed, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 18.27.) That is, publick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons if they be Good, are double bleſſings, as Good men, as Good Magiſtrates; ſuch <hi>wiſe men</hi> eſpecially turne away wrath: Review but thoſe places before alleadged, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Runne too and fro through the ſtreets of Jeruſalem, — and ſee if you can finde a man, if there be any (one) that executeth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I will pardon it.</hi> And ſo of another, it is ſaid, <hi>Then ſtood up</hi> Phineas <hi>and executed judgement, and ſo the plague was ſtayed, Pſal.</hi> 106.30. I ſpeake unto <hi>wiſe men,</hi> judge ye what I ſay. A word to the <hi>wiſe</hi> is enough.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſhewes the <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> of that Family, Towne, City,<note place="margin">2. The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe of places where any Good men.</note> &amp;c. that hath theſe Good and Righteous men amongſt them, if they knew their happineſſe. Many a judgement is prevented, many a bleſſing is procured, or continued for their ſakes, when wicked men know not to whom they are beholding. Theſe are the Towres and Caſtles: Theſe are Walls and Bulwarkes: Theſe are the Forts and Amunition: Theſe are the Horſe-men and Chariots of a Kingdome; and for their ſakes, Townes and Cities are preſerved. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites were beholding to <hi>Lot</hi> for the welfare of their City, ſo long as he was in it, though they acknowledged it not. You know what was ſaid of thoſe two great and holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Elija</hi> and <hi>Eliſha;</hi> when <hi>Elijah</hi> was taken away in a fiery chariot, his ſervant and ſucceſſour <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaw his ſtrength and ſafety, and therefore cried out, <hi>My Father, my Father, the horſemen of Iſrael, and the chariots thereof.</hi> And a King wicked enough, ſaid as much of <hi>Eliſha, My Father, my Father, the horſemen of Iſrael and the chariots thereof,</hi> when he lay a dying. But <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſervant ſaw the reaſon of it, when an army of Souldiers beſet the Towne of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>than,</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111342:11"/> thought to have taken <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and plundered the towne; the ſervant cryes out, alas Maſter, we are undone: <hi>Eliſha</hi> prayes, Lord open his eyes; and preſently he ſaw the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine full of horſes and Chariots of fire, round about <hi>Eliſha.</hi> 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6.17. One <hi>Eliſha</hi> was a better guard then all the hoſts of Iſrael. But I let that paſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. The folly and madneſſe of the world, in 1. Imputing all evills to them.</note>3. It ſhewes the fooliſh unthankfulneſſe, and indeed the folly and madneſſe of the wicked men of the world.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In imputing all their evills and miſeries to Good men, as if they were the cauſes of all the troubles and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that befall them. So they ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Theſe men which are Jewes, trouble our City.</hi> So <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Oratour, elegantly and learnedly charges <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 24.5. <hi>Certainely we have found this man, a peſtilent fellow, (a peſtilence, in the Originall) a mover of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, among all the Jewes, throughout the world, &amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Ahab,</hi> not onely accounts <hi>Elijah</hi> his owne enemy; but alſo charges him, with the miſeries of the times; Art thou he that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles Iſrael? No ſayes he, <hi>It is thou and thy fathers houſe, in that you have forſaken the commandements of the Lord, and thou haſt followed Baalim.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.18. So it was in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, the Chriſtians were charged with all the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that fell upon them: So it is now; All theſe troubles and warres are cauſed by the Puritanes, &amp;c. No, no, it is you that trouble England; your drunkennes and whoredomes, and blaſphemies, &amp;c. theſe are the troublers of England; you that are ſcornefull men, that ſcoffe and deride Godlineſſe, and God himſelf; <hi>That deſpiſe his Miniſters and mock at his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, till there be no remedy.</hi> 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 36.16. It was an hard caſe that <hi>Salomon</hi> tells of; <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.14 15.16. <hi>A little City and few men in it, and a great King came againſt it, and compaſſed it about, and builded forts againſt it; And there was found therein a poore and wiſe man, and he delivered the City by his wiſedome; but none remembred this poore man: Then ſaid I, better is wiſedome then ſtrength; yet the wiſedome of the poor is deſpiſed, and his words are not heard.</hi> That Good men ſhould deliver the Iland, and be forgotten or deſpiſed, is a ſad condition; but that they ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111342:11"/> be charged with the troubles and deſolations of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who are the preſervers of it; this is moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But the madneſſe and unthankfulneſſe of the world appears more yet in perſecuting &amp; baniſhing Good men out of their houſes, Towns, Countries, even out of the world,<note place="margin">2. Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Good</note> if they could. Fooliſh men and unthankfull: They are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to them for all the Good they have; and doe they requite them thus? Is this your kindeneſſe to your friends? As was ſaid to one, many good workes have they done for you, for which of them doe you perſecute and baniſh them? Yea, but what madneſſe is this to ſtop up the fountaines, at leaſt the pipes, through which all the ſtreames of bleſſings come? To pull away the props that uphold a Nation, the pillars that uphold the houſe from falling upon the heads of the owners: To drive the City of all the guards, and pull downe the Forts and Bulwarkes of defence, when an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my comes to beſiege it, this is little leſſe then frenzie. The Sodomites did what they could to drive <hi>Lot</hi> out of their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who alone kept off that ſhowre of fire and brimſtone from them. As <hi>Sampſon</hi> pulling downe the pillars, pulled the houſe upon his owne head: ſo doe theſe haſten their owne deſtruction. If all the Elect were once but gathered out of the world, it would ſoone be all on a flaming fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their eares. Baniſh but all godly men out of a City, Country, &amp;c. and deſolation will ſoone follow. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is noted as a <hi>prognoſticke</hi> and forerunner of ruine, to a place of Kingdome, when righteous men are taken away from the evill to come, <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.1.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is a ground of ſtrong encouragement,<note place="margin">4. Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and comfort.</note> and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, both in ſpeciall to Good men, and generally to this Nation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To Good and Godly men in ſpeciall,<note place="margin">1. To Good men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> that they are thus highly favoured and graced by God, as to make them publick <hi>Goods,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bleſſings</hi> to the places where they live. <hi>Joab</hi> tooke it as a great favour, that King <hi>David</hi> would conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to gratifie him in a requeſt for his owne ſon <hi>Abſalom,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:111342:12"/> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.22. <hi>By this I know that thy ſervant hath found favour in thy ſight, in that the King hath fulfilled the requeſt of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi> What an honour then is it for a poore ſinfull man to have this favour with the King of Heaven, not only to grant the requeſts of his ſervants for themſelves, but when they ſay nothing, even for their ſakes to ſhew mercy unto others? What a ſtrange piece of complement, or rather reall honour was it for God to ſay to <hi>Moſes,</hi> as a man to his friend, <hi>Let me alone that I may deſtroy them,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid nothing that we heare of? What an honour was it to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that without asking, God ſhould give him the life of all the ſoules that ſailed with him? If a man had but ſo much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with a King, it would make him proud, and ſcarce to know the ground he goes on: Why, ſuch honour have all Gods Saints, even to the leaſt of all Saints (as <hi>Paul</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) is this honour given that God can deny them nothing. Marke how <hi>Eliphaz</hi> applies it to <hi>Job</hi> in particular, <hi>Job</hi> 22.30. <hi>The innocent ſhall deliver the Iſland.</hi> True, might he ſay, but whats that to me? Therefore he addes, <hi>And it is delivered by the pureneſſe of thy hands.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, thou being <hi>innocent</hi> and pure, ſhalt have the ſame <hi>Favour,</hi> thou ſhalt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver not thy ſelfe only, but the Iſland. This is the Lords do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To this <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. To this Land and Nation.</note> of ours in generall, it is no leſſe encouragement; That it ſhall not yet be totally deſtroyed, though the ſinnes and ſinners be many, though there be many ſcornfull men, that bring the Land and City into many ſnares, and have enkindled many fires; yet there are many <hi>wiſe men</hi> (bleſſed be the Grace of our God) that is many Good men, that doe helpe to turne away wrath: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithfull <hi>Abrahams,</hi> many righteous <hi>Lots,</hi> many meeke <hi>Moſes's,</hi> many holy <hi>Pauls,</hi> that intercede with God for the Land: If there were any ſweet of comfort to be ſucked out of the gall of bitterneſſe. I meane the wickedneſſe of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, that their deſtruction haſtens a pace, our Enemies are as deſperately wicked, as we could deſire them: But our comfort lies not in their wickedneſſe ſo much as in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111342:12"/> 
               <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of ſome of our owne, or rather in the Goodneſſe and Grace of our God; who for their ſakes uſes to ſhew fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to the places where they live. It is knowne well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, what God would have done to a deſperately wicked City, as any was at that time, yet if there had beene but fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nay but tenne righteous men in <hi>Sodome,</hi> for their ſakes all had been ſpared. We truſt we may ſafely ſay, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any arrogance, there are many fifties, many ten thouſands in this our Land, that never bowed the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> that crie night and day to God that the Iſland may be delivered. Suffer us, O Father of mercies, to plead an argument of thine owne framing, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did for <hi>Sodome,</hi> wee are bad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, perhaps as bad or worſe then <hi>Sodome,</hi> yet ſuffer us ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, to ſpeake but this once; <hi>Wilt thou deſtroy the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with the wicked? Be it farre from thee from doing this thing, to ſlay the righteous with the wicked, and that the righteous ſhould be even as the wicked, be it farre from thee: Shall not the Judge of all the world doe right? Gen.</hi> 18.23.25. Upon this ground we beleeve, though we may have a ſharp ſtorm, yet it will blow over againe. God never yet (and will he beginne now?) deſtroyed an humbling, faſting, praying, reforming Nation. Thoſe Innocents, righteous men, we hope, ſhall deliver the Iſland: Even ſo, Amen.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This may ſerve for a ground of Exhortation,<note place="margin">5. Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and that branches it ſelfe two wayes, to the wicked, and to the Good:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the wicked world, and that in a double reſpect:<note place="margin">
                  <p n="1">1. To wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To the Good.</p>
               </note> Firſt, to ceaſe from evill, and to learn to do well, to labour to become Good &amp; righteous men, even for this reaſon, that as now they are <hi>curſes</hi> and <hi>miſchiefes</hi> to the places where they live, as well as to themſelves, and are branded with this ignominious title of <hi>Incendiaries</hi> of the Kingdome; ſo being Good, they may be honoured as <hi>bleſſings</hi> and <hi>publicke Goods.</hi> This argument <hi>Eliphaz</hi> preſſes <hi>Job</hi> withall, <hi>Job</hi> 22.30. after many other encouragements; Acquaint thy ſelfe now with the Lord, &amp;c. why? becauſe then, thou ſhalt pray unto him and he ſhall heare thee, verſ. 27. And laſt of all, thou ſhalt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111342:13"/> be honoured as the <hi>Deliverer of the Iſland: The innocent ſhall deliver the Iſland, and it is delivered by the pureneſſe of (thy) hands.</hi> The like argument the Lord himſelfe urges upon a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall faſter, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58. that he would faſt to purpoſe, by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting from ſinne and wickedneſſe, and beginne to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and mercifull, <hi>Is not this the Faſt that I have choſen to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, to undoe the heavy burdens, to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that ye breake every yoke? Is it not to deale thy bread to the hungry, &amp;c. Then ſhall thy light breake forth as the morning, and thine health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily, and thy righteouſneſſe ſhall goe before thee, and the glory of the Lord ſhall be thy reward. Then ſhalt thou call, and the Lord ſhall anſwer, &amp;c.</hi> And after all, thus he concludes to our preſent purpoſe, verſ. 12. <hi>And they that ſhall be of thee, ſhall build the old waſte places; thou ſhalt raiſe up the foundations of many generations, and thou ſhalt be called the repairer of the breach, the reſtorer of paths to dwell in.</hi> That is, thou ſhalt be honoured and renowned in preſent and future times, as a man that hath been a publicke Good and a bleſſing to the places where thou livedſt: Thats the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2 To love and make much of thoſe that are Good.</note>2. If we cannot perſwade <hi>ſcornfull men</hi> to be Good them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet let them be perſwaded for their owne ſakes, to make much of thoſe that are Good and righteous: love them and honour them, if not for <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> ſake, yet for your own <hi>Goods</hi> ſake; you are beholding to them for all the <hi>Good</hi> you have and doe enjoy next under God. The Prophet adviſes the people going into Captivity, that they would <hi>ſeeke the peace of that wicked City (Babylon) and pray unto the Lord for it, for</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>in the peace thereof ſhall ye have peace, Jer.</hi> 29.7. And you make much of a bad ſervant, becauſe he is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and beneficiall to you; how much more of thoſe that never did you hurt, that conſtantly doe you Good; preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting judgements and procuring mercies, your very life and livelihood, and all your welfare depends upon it. I leave it to your conſideration; and come,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. To Good men.</note>Secondly, to ſpeake a word of exhortation to <hi>Good men</hi> that they would be <hi>Good</hi> ſtill, and improve all their <hi>intereſt</hi> in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111342:13"/> God in theſe troubleſome and calamitous times for the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Good:</hi> Firſt, to be <hi>Good</hi> ſtill,<note place="margin">1 To b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Good, and better ſtill.</note> and more <hi>Good</hi> as there is more need and uſe for the publicke Good: <hi>He that is holy, let him be holy ſtill, and he that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill.</hi> The better man the greater Good. As we ſee it is the policie of children, when they have any ſute or requeſt to promote, they are commonly <hi>double diligent</hi> to inſinuate themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our affections and favour. It was <hi>Eſthers</hi> wiſdom to ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate herſelf with King <hi>Abaſhueroſh,</hi> when ſhe had a very great requeſt to make unto him; ſhe firſt invites him to a banquet to <hi>ſweeten</hi> his affections to her, inſomuch that he askes her that intended to aske him, <hi>What wilt thou Queen Eſther, what is thy requeſt, and it ſhall be granted thee to the halfe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Eſth.</hi> 5.3. But ſhe hath not yet enough hold of his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, therefore ſhe deſires only that the King would come to the banquet which ſhe had prepared for him; at which time the King makes the ſame demand, What is thy petition, &amp;c. but yet ſhe forbeares, as intending to ingratiate herſelfe more with him; thereupon ſhe renewes her former requeſt, that he would come next day to another banquet, and then ſuppoſing herſelfe endeered to him, out comes her great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, Chap. 7.3. <hi>If I have found favour in thy ſight, O King, and if it pleaſe thee King, let my life be given me at my petition, and my people at my requeſt.</hi> It is worth our imitation in ſuch times of diſtreſſe, when our lives and lands lye at ſtake, to make our way with God, by more exact obſervance of him, to indeere our ſelves unto him, that ſo for our ſakes, not only our owne lives, but our Iſland may be granted at our requeſts. Secondly, to improve all the intereſts they have in God,<note place="margin">2. To im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in God.</note> and all their grace and favour with him (which we have heard is much) for the publicke Good: The King of Heaven can deny you nothing: To what purpoſe is this <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Priviledge</hi> with God, if we make not uſe of it as <hi>Abraham</hi> did? The whole Kingdome and Church of God cries to you as to our Saviour, <hi>If thou canſt do any thing, come &amp; help us?</hi> Ply God with prayers and tears, and be <hi>importunate,</hi> yea in a holy manner <hi>impudent,</hi> till he make this our Land the praiſe and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111342:14"/> glory of all the earth. In a word, imploy your parts and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the publicke Good, which is done by getting publick Spirits: But that leads me to the ſecond branch of my gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Obſervation, to that I now come: And that is this, <hi>Good men are publicke Goods actively:</hi> That is, they are men of publicke Spirits,<note place="margin">2. Branch: Good men are publick Goods actively. This is</note> preferring the Publicke before their own private Good. That this is rightly collected, I referre to the explication of the words, and proceed to the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</note>1. This is Commanded in the Scriptures, as the duty of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian: <hi>Let us do good to all, eſpecially to the houſhold of faith. Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>By love ſerve one another, Gal.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Let no man ſeeke his owne things, but every man anothers wealth, or welfare.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is <hi>Commended</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by inſtances.</note> by the Spirit of God in Scripture, to have been the practiſe of all Good men: we obſerve ſome memorable inſtances. And we beginne with <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Of Moſes.</note> who ſpent himſelf in the publick affaires of the people, in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all cauſes brought before him, till <hi>Jethro</hi> his Father in lawe gave him wiſe counſell. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.17.18. <hi>The things which thou doeſt is not well, thou wilt ſurely weare away, (thou wilt faint and fall) and all this people with thee, for the thing is too heavy for thee, thou art not able to doe it thy ſelfe alone.</hi> And when God offered him one of the greateſt offers that ever was made to a mortall man, to bribe him (that I may ſo ſay) and to take him off from ſeeking and entreating for the Good of his people, he utterly refuſed it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.9, 10, 11, <hi>&amp;c. The Lord ſaid unto Moſes, I have ſeen this people, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it is a ſtiffenecked people. Now therefore let me alone, that my wrath may waxe hot againſt them, and conſume them, and I will make of thee a mighty people. But</hi> Moſes <hi>prayed unto the Lord his God, &amp;c.</hi> And another time, when the Lord ſeemed reſolved to deſtroy that people, he ventures not only his life but his <hi>ſoule</hi> between them and the wrath of God: <hi>If thou wilt pardon this people, well; if not, blot me out of thy Book, &amp;c.</hi> The like we may obſerve in <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Of David.</note> 
               <hi>He fed the people with a true heart, and ruled them prudently with all his power, Pſal.</hi> 7, 72.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111342:14"/> And as if the ſpirit of <hi>Moſes</hi> had been upon him, he expoſes himſelfe to the ſword of the deſtroying Angel to ſtay it from the people, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.17, <hi>Behold I have ſinned, yea I have done wickedly,</hi> (takes all the fault upon himſelfe, and all the puniſhment too) <hi>but theſe ſheep what have they done? Let thine hand I pray thee be againſt me and my fathers houſe.</hi> This is the commendation of that Good man <hi>Jehojada</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>3. Of Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jada.</p>
                  <p>2 Chron. 24.16.</p>
               </note> the high Prieſt, and the <hi>Epitaph</hi> upon his grave, made by the Spirit of God, <hi>They buried him in the City of</hi> David <hi>amongſt the Kings, becauſe he had done good in</hi> Iſraell <hi>both towards God, and towards his houſe. Mordecai</hi> alſo was a man of the like ſpirit, whoſe life and ſtory is concluded with this Elegie, <hi>He was next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King, and great among the Jewes, and accepted of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his brethren.</hi> There is his Greatneſſe, his Goodneſſe followes, <hi>Seeking the wealth of the people, and ſpeaking peace to all his people, Eſth.</hi> 10.3. But moſt memorable is the inſtance of that Good and Great man <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Of Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah.</note> who living in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a King, and in all pleaſures of a <hi>Court,</hi> yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed not himſelfe, whileſt he underſtood the miſeries of his people, and the Deſolations of the houſe of God, and of his City, as in <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1. and 2. Chapters, may eaſily appeare. But the diſcovery of his publick ſpirit, with neglect of all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts, is moſt remarkeable, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.14. Twelve yeares together; <hi>from the twentieth yeare, even unto the two and thirtieth of King</hi> Artaxerxes, <hi>that is, twelve yeares. I and my brethren have not eaten the bread of the Governour. For the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Governours that were before me, had been chargeable to the people, and had taken of them bread and wine, beſides forty ſhekels of ſilver, yea, and their ſervants bare rule over the people,</hi> (as great mens ſervants uſe to doe) <hi>but ſo did not I, becauſe of the feare of God.</hi> But then, it may be, as he had nothing, ſo hee did nothing, but only overſee the people: For that, ſee what follows, verſe 16. <hi>Yet alſo I continued in the worke of this wall, —and all my ſervants were gathered thither unto the worke.</hi> That is, though neither I nor my ſervants had any allowance, yet we were as active and diligent in the maine worke, as they that tooke wages for their worke. But perhaps hee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111342:15"/> had a great eſtate or revenue of his owne, and improved that to his owne beſt advantage: There were many poor Jews that were glad for neceſſity, to ſell their inheritances, and ſo he made good bargaines for himſelfe by buying land at the cheapeſt rate: No, ſayes he, <hi>We bought no land,</hi> as ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did: And leſt any man ſhould thinke, though he did not get by the publicke calamities, yet he might ſave his owne eſtate, by living privately, and below his eſtate, and the dignity of a Governour; he addes, <hi>Moreover there were at my table an hundred and fifty of the (poore) Jewes and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, beſides thoſe that came unto us from among the Heathen that are about us,</hi> verſe 17. His charge and expences is ſet downe in the 18. verſe to be very great; <hi>Yet for all this required not I the bread of the Governour, becauſe the bondage was great upon this people.</hi> All theſe conſidered, you will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde a man of ſo publicke a ſpirit in all the Scripture. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one we finde in the new Teſtament, that comes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing neare him in ſpirituall reſpects, and that is Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Of Paul.</note> firſt he ſayes, he had upon him the care of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Secondly, he laboured more then all the Apoſtles, ſpared no paines, feared no dangers, ran through many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities and hazards, by ſea and land, by brethren and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, &amp;c. Thirdly, though he might have beene chargeable as an Apoſtle of Chriſt, and had power to eat and drinke, and to carry about a ſiſter, a wife, as other Apoſtles did; yet he uſed not this power, but preached the Goſpell freely; and leſt he might be chargeable, he wrought with his own hands to ſupply his neceſſities; and as he ſought not his owne profit, but the profit of many, that they might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. laſt; ſo ſpent himſelfe in the publicke ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, venturing his owne life for the Good of the Church: <hi>I count not my life deare to me, ſo that I may finiſh my courſe with joy, Act.</hi> 20.24. <hi>Yea</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>and if I be offered (powred forth as a drinke offering</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>upon the ſacrifice and ſervice of your faith, I joy and rejoyce with you all, Phil.</hi> 2.17. And (to omit many things of like kinde) that there might be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and inſtance of one under the New Teſtament, not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111342:15"/> inferiour to the higheſt in the Old, heare what he ſaies like another <hi>Moſes,</hi> if not beyond him) <hi>I have great heavineſſe and continuall ſorrow in my heart; For I could wiſh that my ſelfe were accurſed from Chriſt, for my brethren, my kinſmen according to the fleſh, Rom.</hi> 9.2, 3. We need ſay no more, we have given inſtances of all ſorts, Kings, Prieſts, Magiſtrates, Miniſters, of eminently publicke ſpirits, to make good our aſſertion, <hi>That Good men are publicke Goods Actively, as well as Paſſively:</hi> That is, men of publicke ſpirits, active for the publick Good, though paſſive in neglect of themſelves. Doe but take the Reaſons<note place="margin">3. Grounded on Good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> of it, and we ſhall haſten to the Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Good men are made partakers of the divine Nature,<note place="margin">1. They par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature.</note> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. and ſo made conformable to God, their heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, and to Chriſt their Head. The <hi>Proverb</hi> is, <hi>A Good the more common it is, the better it is:</hi> we may invert it, The better any thing is, the more communicative it is of it ſelfe; God himſelfe, the beſt and greateſt Good, communicates himſelfe to all his creatures, with no reſpect of any profit to himſelfe. <hi>The eyes of all things wait upon thee, O Lord, and thou giveſt them their meat in due ſeaſon, Pſal.</hi> 145.15. <hi>Thou openeſt thy hand, and filleſt with thy bleſſing every living thing. Thou art Good, and doeſt Good, Pſal.</hi> 119.68. <hi>The Lord is Good to all, and his mercy is over all his workes, Pſal.</hi> 145.9. <hi>He makes his Sunne to ſhine upon the Good and the bad, and his raine to fall upon the juſt and unjuſt.</hi> The Lord Jeſus alſo is called the <hi>common Salvation, Jude</hi> verſe 3. <hi>He went about doing Good, and healing every diſeaſe.</hi> He gave himſelfe for all his ſheep and wholly for every one: <hi>Who loved me and gave himſelfe for me,</hi> ſaies <hi>Paul,</hi> as if he had loved and dyed for none but him: <hi>O bone Jeſu, &amp;c.</hi> as that Father in a ſweet meditation, and Soliloquie of his, <hi>O ſweet Saviour Jeſus, who takeſt care for all of us, as if we were but one man, and ſo for every one, as for all?</hi> Chriſt pleaſed not himſelfe, ſought not his owne profit, his owne glory, but the ſalvation of his people. <hi>Let the ſame minde be in you, that was in Chriſt Jeſus, Phil.</hi> 2.5. And ſo it is in ſome proportion; the ſame nature, the ſame mind, and ſo followers of God as deare children, and of Chriſt their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111342:16"/> Head, and ſo communicative of their Goodneſſe to others: The ground of this in God, is his Al-ſufficiency partly, hee needs not the Good of any creature, and partly his Great Goodneſſe, whereof he is ſo full, that as the Sea empties it ſelfe into the ſprings and rivers, ſo doth he communicate his Goodnes to the creatures. Good men then being made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Al-ſufficient and Good God, are like him in this, to ſeeke the publicke Good, with neglect of themſelves: and thats the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Grace en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges the heart.</note>2. Grace and Goodneſſe enlarges the heart, and hand, and all: So the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11, 12, 13. <hi>O ye Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, our mouth is opened to you, our heart is enlarged; ye are not ſtraitned in us, but ye are ſtraitned in your owne bowels: Bee ye alſo enlarged.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, it is your fault that you have no more benefit by us; you are not capable of what we are able and willing to give: And ſo to his Theſſalonians, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Being affectionately deſirous of you, we were willing to have imparted to you, not the Goſpel of God only, but alſo our owne ſoules, becauſe ye were deare unto us.</hi> It is obſervable, that is noted of thoſe firſt converts, who were before ſtrait-hearted and ſtrait-handed, but when once made partakers of the Grace of God, how much they were enlarged, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there any among them that lacked; for as many as were poſſeſſours of lands or houſes, ſold them, and brought the prices of the things that were ſold: And laid them downe at the Apoſtles feet, and diſtribution was made to every man, according as he had need, Act.</hi> 4.34, 35. And before that, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.44. <hi>All that beleeved were together, and had all things common. Omnia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreta apud nos praeter uxores,</hi> ſaid <hi>Tertullian</hi> of his times, All things with us, are common, except wives.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Grace ſets up another end.</note>3. Grace alters and ſets up another <hi>End</hi> in a man, that is Gods <hi>Glory</hi> in the publicke <hi>Good,</hi> for therein is Gods Glory moſt conſpicuous. Our ends are private in Nature, we are our owne Alpha and Omega; our ſelves are beginning and ending to our owne ſelves, our owne god, ſelfiſh in all, as they ſay; Self-ends, Self-profit, Self-honour, &amp;c. Now the firſt Leſſon in the Schoole of Chriſt is, <hi>Self-deniall,</hi> let him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111342:16"/> deny himſelfe, his owne reaſon, his owne will, his owne affections, his owne ends. Marke what a new <hi>End</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſets up, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Whether therefore ye eat or drink, or whatſoever you doe, doe all to the glory of God:</hi> And then, that you may ſee he meanes the Glory of God in the publicke Good; he addes in the laſt verſe, <hi>Even as I pleaſe all men in all things, not ſeeking mine owne profit, but the profit of many that they may be ſaved.</hi> A naturall man called out to publicke ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, is ready to plead his owne private intereſts: as the trees did in <hi>Jothams</hi> parable, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.9. <hi>Should I leave my fatneſſe ſaies the Olive tree: Should I leave my ſweetneſſe, ſaies the Fig tree, or I leave my wine ſaies the Vine, to be promoted over the trees.</hi> The words rendered <hi>to be promoted over the trees,</hi> are ſignificant in the <hi>Hebrew, to goe up and downe for (other) trees?</hi> That is, Shall I neglect my ſelfe, my owne profit, my owne honour, my owne pleaſure, to runne up and downe (as a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate or a publicke perſon muſt) to doe others ſervice? It is a common and received <hi>Proverbe</hi> in nature, <hi>proximus ego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met mihi,</hi> I am my owne next neighbour: and that is another much alike, <hi>Charity begins at home.</hi> And a third is as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>Every man for himſelfe, and God (only) for all.</hi> Thus indeed ſpeaks nature, but Grace clean otherwiſe, as you have heard; we are Selfe-ends, and Selfe-gods, in nature; In Grace, <hi>Homo homini Deus,</hi> every man is a <hi>God</hi> to another: that's a third.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Good man is made a member of the body myſticall:<note place="margin">4. They are members of the body my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall.</note> Now as it is in nature, every member of the body naturall, ſerves not it ſelfe alone, but is a ſervant to the whole body; The eye ſees, not for it ſelfe (ſees not it ſelfe) but for the whole body, the hand workes not, the foot moves not for it ſelfe, but for the whole body: So it ſhould be in the body politicall, ſo it is in the body myſticall, every member is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the community: More might be added, but theſe ſhall ſuffice for the preſent, and ſo we come to Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.<note place="margin">4. Applied.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Uſe ſhall be for <hi>Diſcovery</hi> (and this is a time of great <hi>Diſcoveries</hi>) of bad and naughty hearts.<note place="margin">1. For diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of bad hearts.</note> Before wee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111342:17"/> come to particulars, we may juſtly take up the complaint of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Helpe Lord, for there is not a Godly man left, the faithfull are miniſhed from among the ſonnes of men.</hi> That is, if we look upon the generality of men, there will be but a few Good men be found: we may make the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> by theſe two things: 1. That many have <hi>publicke ſpirits</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but for <hi>publicke miſchiefes:</hi> 2. That many have <hi>private ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> in publick cauſes: we will note ſome particu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ars briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. Publick miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, as</note>1. There are many, that have <hi>Publick</hi> Spirits, not for the publick Good, but for publick evill, to the places where they live, juſt like the bramble in <hi>Jothams</hi> parable, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.14.15. choſen to raigne over the trees, who did ſcratch and catch all for it ſelfe. <hi>Publico malo nati:</hi> as if they were borne for publick miſchiefe; like <hi>Paris,</hi> whoſe mother <hi>Hecuba</hi> dream'd, when ſhe was with child of him, that ſhe was delivered of a <hi>burning firebrand;</hi> and ſo he proved to his Country, if ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſay true; For through his meanes, the City <hi>Troy,</hi> was ſet on fire, and the Country ruined. Such <hi>firebrands,</hi> there are many now to be found, who have ſet this (as well as other) Kingdomes on <hi>fire,</hi> or brought Townes, Cities, Countries, into a <hi>ſnare,</hi> as our text ſpeakes: we note ſome.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. Papiſts and Jeſuites.</note>1. As firſt, <hi>Papiſts,</hi> home-borne <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who are the <hi>vipers</hi> that moſt unnaturally have endeavoured to eate through their mothers bowels. Not their nature onely, but their Religion alſo, teaches and allowes them for the Good of the <hi>Catholike cauſe,</hi> falſely ſo called, not to ſpare their owne native Country, their owne kindred, Brothers, Fathers, no not of their own Religion, if it be for the publick Good, of their falſe Religion. To blow up Parliaments, to ruine Cities, Countries, Kingdomes, is their ordinary worke. Eſpecially of thoſe, whom they call <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> the <hi>Bellowes</hi> of Hell, the <hi>Incendiaries</hi> of Chriſtendome, at this day. The <hi>Curſe</hi> of God is upon them fearefully for arrogating their Name from <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which ſignifies a Saviour, and is impropriated to the Sonne of God: <hi>Thou ſhalt call his name Jeſus.</hi> Theſe men, that call themſelves <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> are, by the juſt judgement of God upon them, the <hi>Deſtroyers</hi> of Cities, Countries,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111342:17"/> Kingdomes, and might farre better take their name from him, who is called in Hebrew Abaddon, and in Greeke Apolluon, but ſignifying a Deſtroyer. <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next to theſe, are thoſe, (propheſied to fall into theſe laſt and worſt times: 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.) whom the Apoſtle calls Traitours.<note place="margin">2. Traitours to their Country.</note> 
               <hi>In the laſt dayes ſhall come perillous times, for men ſhall be lovers of themſelves, Proud, boaſters, Traytors:</hi> Not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the publike truſt, but even their owne Countries and Kingdomes. Wofull experience have theſe our ſad times, of theſe publick miſchiefes: who have forſaken their faith, betrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the charges wherwith they were entruſted, and with them, as much as in them laye, betrayed their Religion, Laws, Liberties, and which is moſt unnaturall, themſelves, and their Poſterities to perpetuall miſerie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Adde to theſe, thoſe of our text, <hi>proud, ſcornfull</hi> men,<note place="margin">3. Seditious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piri s.</note> who by ſtirring up <hi>Seditions,</hi> and ſtrife, in Townes and Cities, have ſet all places almoſt on fire: <hi>Onely by pride men make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: Prov.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Caſt out the ſcorner, and contention ſhall goe out: Prov.</hi> 22.10. <hi>Yea ſtrife and reproach ſhall ceaſe.</hi> Such an one was that <hi>Silver-ſmith Demetrius, Acts</hi> 19. who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of defence of religion, (but indeed for his own gaine) ſet all the City of <hi>Epheſus</hi> on an uproare. Such ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Achitophel,</hi> who adoring the riſing <hi>Sunne,</hi> fomented that <hi>Sedition</hi> and Rebellion of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> out of his owne <hi>Ambition,</hi> to ingratiate, and advance himſelfe, with that yong Prince. All times, &amp; eſpecially theſe of ours, have exemplified theſe <hi>Incendiaries;</hi> the pride and <hi>ſcorn</hi> of ſome, have ſtirred up ſo much contention, and kindled ſo great a flame, that all the <hi>Wiſe men;</hi> of the Kingdome know not well how to quench it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Amongſt theſe may be reckoned, a multitude of men who are <hi>Publick enemies</hi> to the State and Kingdome: As firſt, <hi>Oppreſſours,</hi> and <hi>Depopulators,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, &amp;c.</note> who do not, as they of old, in the Prophet, adde houſe to houſe, or town to town, but pull down houſe after houſe, and towne after towne, till there be no place, for a poore man to dwell neere them, till at laſt they pull downe their owne houſes, and deſtroy their owne families, that their place cannot be found. So that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111342:18"/> curſe is now made good upon many of them; <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus ſaith the Lord, many houſes great and faire ſhall be left deſolate without an inhabitant, Iſay.</hi> 5.9. Such are the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors,</hi> the <hi>Monopoliſts</hi> of later times, who under pretence of <hi>Publick Good,</hi> have enriched themſelves, with the <hi>ſpoiles</hi> of the Commonwealth: Theſe and ſuch like, are the <hi>Catter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers</hi> and locuſts of the places and Countries where they live; and as the Father ſaid of <hi>Ingroſſers</hi> of corne that made a famine in plentie, <hi>mercatores humanarum cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum,</hi> the <hi>Merchants</hi> of humane miſeries and calamities. In a word, all <hi>Polititians</hi> that drive their owne <hi>deſignes,</hi> at the publick charges in publick places of imployment; Men, like that unjuſt Steward in the Goſpell, who being entruſted with the publick Treaſure, for an hundred write down foureſcore, perhaps but fifty; diverting the publick ſtocke into their owne purſes, to make themſelves rich, in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick poverty of the State. This is, as if a man in a ſhip, in a ſtorme, when all is like to be caſt away, ſhould gather all the wealth of the ſhip into his owne cabine; or as if the ſtomack a publick officer in the body natural, ſhould keep all the meat to it ſelfe, and ſtarve the whole body. Well fare yet that Noble ſpirited <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> we ſpake of before, that was ſo farre from eating the bread of the people, <hi>That he did not eate the bread of the Governour; becauſe the bondage was great up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people. Nehem.</hi> 5.17.18. Well fare alſo thoſe juſt Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, thoſe faithfull and honeſt Treaſurers, entruſted with the publick ſtock; 2. <hi>King.</hi> 12.15. <hi>and</hi> 22.7. <hi>They reckoned not with the men, into whoſe hands they delivered the mony, to bee beſtowed on workemen, for they dealt faithfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Private<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Spirits.</note>2. As there are many evill publick ſpirits; ſo alſo many private evill ſpirits, in the publick cauſes of God and the State: (Not to ſpeake of <hi>Idle</hi> perſons, our lazie <hi>Gallants,</hi> in times of peace, that conferre nothing to the publick Good, by any publick uſefull imployment, as all creatures in the world doe, beſides themſelves,) We may take up the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21. <hi>All ſeeke their owne, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And we may ſee his propheſie
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111342:18"/> fulfilled. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.2. <hi>In the laſt dayes ſhall come perilous times, For men ſhall be lovers of their owne ſelves:</hi> why were not men ever <hi>Lovers</hi> of themſelves? Is it any ſuch great fault or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous for men to love themſelves? Is it not naturall for <hi>charity to begin at home?</hi> True, but the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> means, that in the laſt times, men ſhal be Lovers of themſelves, ſo that they ſhal Love no body elſe, not their owne poſterity, not their owne Country; and therefore it followes in a few words after, men ſhall be Lovers of themſelves—<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without naturall affection:</hi> So they may but ſave themſelves and ſleepe in a whole skin, let poſterity take care for it ſelfe, let the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity ſinke or ſwimme, they care not. Of this ſort are all <hi>Newters,</hi> and at beſt <hi>unwilling contributers,</hi> to the publicke cauſes of God and his people, either with their eſtates or perſons. Firſt, for eſtates, men of a covetous churliſh diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion like <hi>Nabal,</hi> who when <hi>David</hi> ſent meſſengers to him for ſome reliefe and refreſhment of himſelfe and his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who were a protection to his cattell and ſervants, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned this dogged anſwer, <hi>Shall I take my bread and my wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and my fleſh, provided for the ſhearers of my ſheep, and give it to men I know not from whence they are? There be many ſervants now adaies, that break away from their maſters, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. Shall I leave my <hi>fatneſſe</hi> ſayes the Olive? my <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> ſayes the Figtree, &amp;c. to go to be promoted over the trees? Shall I leave my profit, my honour, my pleaſure, for other mens ſakes? Marke (I pray) what a ſcornfull anſwer the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> and <hi>Penuel</hi> gave to <hi>Gideon</hi> that fought for them, when he ſpake to them for ſome reliefe for his fainting fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Give I pray you loves of bread unto the people that are faint.</hi> They anſwer him with a flout &amp; a jeer, <hi>Are the hands of Zeba and Zalmunna, now in thine hands, that thou ſayeſt, Give bread, &amp;c.</hi> How many are there that in this great and publick <hi>Cauſe</hi> now in agitation, have never yet contributed any thing, (willingly) but ill words, <hi>mocks</hi> and <hi>jeers,</hi> though they have enjoyed the benefit of publicke <hi>ſafety,</hi> they and theirs? To whom it may be ſaid, as <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Nabal, In vaine have I kept all that this fellow had in the wilderneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:111342:19"/> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.21. Theſe men perhaps, ſome of them, wiſh all were well, but lend not the leaſt aſſiſtance that all may bee well: Sit ſtill, and live to themſelves, and enjoy their owne eſtates; even this diſcovers men to be <hi>Naught,</hi> becauſe they have ſuch narrow, ſuch private ſpirits in publicke Cauſes. Let <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> ſtand or fall, ſo they may but have <hi>peace</hi> upon any conditions, ſo it coſt them nothing. And ſo for their <hi>perſons</hi> to be engaged in the publick ſervice, how few are there that offer themſelves willingly to the worke? Men ſtrive not who ſhall goe, but who ſhall not goe to the warres; what ſhuffling to avoid it when called forth? what ſtarting backe, what running away, when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny danger appears? what <hi>Apologies</hi> and excuſes for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. It hath it ſeems been the faſhion of former times as well as this? See but an Inſtance in <hi>Judg.</hi> 5 14, 15, 16. where <hi>Deborah</hi> firſt diſcovers the <hi>Voluntiers, Out of Ephraim was there a root of them againſt Amalek; after thee Benjamin among thy people out of Machir came down Governours, out of Zebulon they that handle the pen of the writer. And the Princes of Iſſachar were with Deborah: even Iſſachar and alſo Barak, he was ſent on foot into the valley:</hi> But then there were many Newters of other Tribes, <hi>For the diviſions of Ruben were great ſearchings of heart.</hi> Great ſearchings of heart? for what? to finde excuſes and pretences for their Newtrality and Cowardlyneſſe: So it followes, verſe 16. <hi>Why abodeſt thou</hi> (Ruben) <hi>amongſt the ſheepfolds, to heare the bleatings of the flocks? for the diviſions of Ruben, there were great ſearchings of heart. Gilead abode beyond Iordan, and why did Dan abide in ſhips? Aſher continued on the ſea ſhore, and abode in his breaches.</hi> The meaning (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) may be this, when theſe tribes ſhould have gone free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the warres, after <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barac,</hi> they tarried all at home, and had great ſearchings of heart how to anſwer it, if objected againſt them: Some, they had flocks of ſheep to look to; ſome could not get over Jordan; ſome were in their ſhips of merchandiſe; ſome repairing their breaches, &amp;c. thus they framed their excuſes, ſome had one impediment, ſome another. Juſt the caſe of theſe times, in the publicke
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111342:19"/> cauſe of Religion, &amp;c. ſome have land to plow; ſome have harveſt to get home; ſome have a wife to pleaſe; ſome have houſes and flocks to guard or ſecure, which will be plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed if they appeare in the quarrell; ſome are poore, and have wife and children to maintaine: For the diviſions of <hi>England,</hi> there are great ſearchings of heart. Theſe all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their private ſpirits, and little Good hearts. But mark what followes, <hi>Zebulon and Naphtali were a people that jeopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their lives unto the death in the high places of the field,</hi> verſe 18. and ſo ſhewed themſelves, both <hi>Good men</hi> and <hi>Good patriots.</hi> And this may ſerve for the firſt Uſe of Diſcovery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is for <hi>direction,</hi> in our choice of fit <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for <hi>publicke places</hi> and imployments.<note place="margin">2. Uſe: For direction in choice of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Chuſe a man of a <hi>Publicke ſpirit;</hi> that is to ſay, chuſe a Good man, and one that is truly Religious, for ſuch onely are men of publicke ſpirits, for the publicke Good. For example, Firſt, in choice of a Miniſter, a publicke perſon; (a buſineſſe of great and common concernment in theſe times) If you would chuſe one that ſhal be faithfull &amp; conſtant to you, chuſe not a man of a narrow or private ſpirit: one that is either covetous, or ambitious, or voluptuous, that ſeekes himſelfe and his own ends, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt: ſuch an one will ſeeke <hi>yours,</hi> not you; and when he hath found what he ſeeks, will but a little care for the flock. Amongſt other qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Miniſter, the Apoſtle requires, that he be not <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous given to filthy lucre, not given to wine,</hi> not voluptuous: A Good man onely will make a Good Miniſter: as it is ſaid of <hi>Barnabas, He was a Good man, and full of the holy Ghoſt and of faith, and much people was added to the Lord, Act.</hi> 11.24. A Good Miniſter is a good <hi>light,</hi> a <hi>lampe,</hi> a <hi>candle</hi> that ſpends himſelfe in giving light to others, whereas a <hi>ſnuffe</hi> burnes and lights only within its owne ſocket, but is darke and ſtinking to others round about him. In a word, a Good Miniſter is like that Good Shepheard that layes downe his life for his ſheep. Secondly, it may give us <hi>direction</hi> alſo in choice of publicke <hi>Officers, Magiſtrates, Commanders, Knights</hi> of the Shire, and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> of Parliament, if ever we
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111342:20"/> live to another election, to ſeeke out and chuſe men of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke ſpirits; who are they? you will ſay: why (ſay the world what they pleaſe) they are <hi>Good</hi> men, truly <hi>Godly</hi> men; they will be conſtant and faithfull in their entruſtments, they will live and dye for you, and with you: All other men will warpe and ſtart aſide like a deceitfull bow, will be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted or wrought like wax to take any impreſſion of his owne or others deſignes. Experience hath taught us ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this particular: In theſe great <hi>diviſions</hi> of this ſtate, what <hi>diſcoveries</hi> have been made of falſe &amp; faithleſſe hearts? In our great <hi>Senate,</hi> in our Armies, in all publick ſervices: what ſtrange <hi>diſcoveries</hi> have beene made of thoſe perhaps, whom wee little ſuſpected. They ſay in politicks, <hi>A man may be an ill man, yet a Good Citizen.</hi> I am ſure it is falſe in Divinity. He that is an <hi>ill</hi> man, can no more be a <hi>Good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot,</hi> a <hi>Good</hi> Commonwealths man, then <hi>evill</hi> can be <hi>Good.</hi> He may perhaps be ſeemingly Good in times of peace, when no diviſions, no temptations: but no man will be conſtantly faithfull, but he that is a man of a publicke ſpirit, and no man but a <hi>Good</hi> man hath a publicke ſpirit. Let it be a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to us for the preſent, and for the future, in choice of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny publick Inſtruments; if we be againe deceived, we may thanke our ſelves. All, or a great part of theſe preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions of our ſtate ariſe from hence, that men in publicke places have <hi>private</hi> ſpirits, private <hi>ends</hi> and aimes with neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the publicke.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Uſet double honour due to men of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſpirits.</note>3. This may informe us, what <hi>Honour</hi> and eſtimation is due to <hi>Good men,</hi> men of publicke ſpirits, that neglect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the <hi>publicke Good,</hi> their owne profit, pleaſure, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Truly, what the Apoſtle ſpeakes of laborious and painfull <hi>Miniſters, That the Elders that rule well, are worthy or to be accounted worthy of double Honour, eſpecially they that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the word and doctrine,</hi> is fairly by proportion, to be applyed to all publicke Inſtruments of publicke ſpirits. Men of <hi>private</hi> places, with <hi>publick</hi> ſpirits, are worthy of double honour, eſpecially thoſe who being imployed in <hi>publick</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, doe labour, and even ſpend themſelves, and what they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111342:20"/> have for the Good and welfare of the Community. And what is that double honour? Countenance and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſay ſome: A <hi>lampe</hi> or candle that conſumes it ſelf to give others light (as every faithfull Miniſter doth) deſerves to be ſet, not under a bed or a buſhell, but upon a Table, as our Saviour ſpeakes; there's his <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>Countenance,</hi> and to be plentifully ſupplyed with oyle, to preſerve it ſelfe for the common Good, there's the <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>Maintenance.</hi> The like is due to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> that is imployed in the publicke ſervices of the State; and to the Souldier that jeopards his life in the high places of the field, to preſerve the lives of thouſands. It is an odious and ignominious <hi>ſhame,</hi> that we ſhould chuſe men to imploy in our publicke and common Concernments, ſpirituall or temporall, (who muſt leave their <hi>fatneſſe</hi> and their <hi>ſweetnes,</hi> and their wine, (as the trees ſpeak in the parable) which they might privately, &amp; with eaſe enjoy as well as we) and then when we have ſo done, deſert them, both in regard of <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> or aſſiſtance: This hath been the caſe of many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in times paſt, and at the preſent, the condition of our Honourable Patriots in Parliament: How ſhamefully have they been deſerted (I wiſh that were all, yea maligned, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed at by <hi>Scornfull men,</hi> hated, oppoſed) even by them that choſe, and imployed them. If men go on thus to forſake them, and let them fall, for want of <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> it is juſt with God, they ſhould never chuſe more, or never live to partake of that common Good, which they deſire and endeavour to do for them. As therefore the Apoſtle ſpake in a caſe of a faithfull Miniſter, ſo I of all of a publicke ſpirit, <hi>Receive them therefore in the Lord, with all gladneſſe, and hold ſuch in reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe for the worke of Chriſt, they were neare unto death, not regarding their owne life, to ſupply your lacke of ſervice, Phil.</hi> 2.29.30. And as <hi>Deborah</hi> gave her <hi>Voluntiers</hi> their due and double Honour, ſo let us doe alſo; Heare what ſhe ſayes, <hi>My heart is towards the Governours of Iſrael, that offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves willingly among the people; Bleſſe ye the Lord, Judg.</hi> 5.9. and ſo ſhe goes on to name the tribes and perſons, caſting a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111342:21"/> ſecret reproach upon the <hi>Newters;</hi> and at laſt come to it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: <hi>Zebulon and Naphtali were a people that jeoparded their lives unto the death in the high places of the field,</hi> verſe 18. So ſay I, my heart is towards the Governours of England, our <hi>Parliament Patriots,</hi> that offered themſelves willingly among the people: <hi>Bleſſe ye the Lord.</hi> Bleſſe ye the Lord that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up their perſons, and their ſpirits, to ſtand for the publick Good of <hi>Religion, Lawes</hi> and <hi>Liberties;</hi> and to ſpend their time, their ſtrength, their eſtates, their credits and honour, and lives for the ſame: And bleſſed be they of the Lord, and their poſterities after them for ever. My heart is alſo towards thoſe <hi>Noble Commanders</hi> and common <hi>Souldiers,</hi> that have offered themſelves willingly among the people, and have jeoparded their lives in the high places of the field, bleſſe ye the Lord that raiſed up their ſpirits to ſuch a pitch of <hi>Magnanimity</hi> and <hi>Reſolution,</hi> and bleſſed be they of the Lord; let their lives and names be precious with the Lord, and with the generations to come. Laſtly, my heart is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Honourable City</hi> and <hi>Citizens,</hi> that offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their eſtates willingly among and above all the Cities of the Kingdome, to the almoſt exhauſting of their wealth and treaſure, to the publick Good of the whole Land: Bleſſe ye the Lord, that ſtirred them up; and bleſſed be they of the Lord for ever: the Lord recompence it upon them and theirs ſevenfold. This is the leaſt we can doe for them, that have bn <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of the <hi>publick Good:</hi> Render to every one their due Honour to whom Honour belongeth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It may be a ground of <hi>Exhortation</hi> to all, <hi>eſpecially</hi> to thoſe who are <hi>publicke</hi> perſons,<note place="margin">4 Uſe: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion to get pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licke ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rits.</note> to ſtudy and endeavour the publicke Good, above their owne, with neglect of their owne ſometimes; and to this end, to labour for publicke ſpirits: every man to contribute his abilities of what kinde ſoever, to be ſerviceable to the Community. As above in the heavens, every Starre, even the leaſt contributes its light and influence to the world, eſpecially thoſe of greater <hi>magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude:</hi> So let it be on earth, in a Church, in a State, every one caſt in ſomething to the publicke <hi>Treaſury:</hi> Some their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111342:21"/> 
               <hi>wiſdome</hi> and parts: Some their <hi>eſtates:</hi> Some their <hi>ſtrength:</hi> Some their <hi>perſons</hi> and lives; all their prayers.<note place="margin">1. Perſwaded.</note> For the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading of this, conſider theſe things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. We cannot (as hath been ſaid) otherwiſe approve our ſelves to God, to men, or to our owne conſciences,<note place="margin">1. This an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of Goodneſſe.</note> that we are Good men, have any true Goodneſſe, true Grace, true Religion. A <hi>Good</hi> man is a publicke <hi>Good,</hi> both <hi>Paſſively</hi> and <hi>Actively;</hi> is Good, and doth Good: A private ſpirit is an evidence of a naturall heart. It was not a good ſpeech of the trees in the parable; Shall I leave my fatneſſe or my ſweetneſſe, &amp;c. to be promoted over the trees, to goe up and downe for other trees? we muſt, if we be trees of Gods Paradiſe, of Gods planting. <hi>He ſhall be like a tree planted by the waters ſide, that brings forth his fruit in his ſeaſon, Pſal.</hi> 1. All times a reſeaſonable for a Chriſtians fruit, and ſo are all places: He hath his fruit in private, but moſt in publick.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is the end of all our <hi>Abilities;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. It is the end of all abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</note> 
               <hi>Non nobis ſolum nati, &amp;c.</hi> is a <hi>Proverbiall</hi> ſpeech amongſt the very Heathens: we were not borne for our ſelves, nor live for our ſelves; our parents challenge a part, our kindred and friends a part, our Country, our Religion, all: We are but Stewards entruſted with our Maſters Treaſure, to be diſtributed and layd out for the Good of the familie: We are but Servants or <hi>Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that have nothing properly our owne; we come into the world to ſerve our generation: It is the Scripture phraſe, ſpoken of a King, King <hi>David,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.36. <hi>When he had ſerved his generation, he fell aſleepe.</hi> In the great world, all creatures <hi>contribute</hi> their ſhare to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Communitie: No creature is made for it ſelfe, none acts for it ſelfe, none lives to it ſelfe but an idle perſon, and a Newter. The ſheepe, and bees, and the reſt, pay their tribute to Man, <hi>Sic vos non vobis, &amp;c.</hi> and the bees in the hives do not fill their cells with hony for their owne private uſe, but every owne brings in, and layes up, as in a common treaſurie; and drones are either killed, or baniſhed from that little Commonwealth: In the body <hi>naturall,</hi> every member is a publick ſervant, to the whole <hi>Corporation.</hi> And ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111342:22"/> 
               <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the body <hi>myſticall,</hi> or Citizens in the body <hi>politicall,</hi> vary from all the reſt, and live only to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is very <hi>reaſonable:</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. It is very Reaſonable.</note> There's none but lives upon the common ſtocke, none but deſires to partake, and ſhare, in the Publick Good, of peace, plenty, liberty, lawes, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: what reaſon or equitie, they ſhould expect it, if they contribute nothing to it. Shall all other men, all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs be made ſerviceable to them, and they to no body? How can men deſire of God with the Pſalmiſt? <hi>That they may ſee the Good of his choſen, that they may rejoice in the gladneſſe of his nation, that they may glory with his inheritance,</hi> Pſal. 106.5. if they have not ſome way or other lent their aſſiſtance to the procuring of it. If they will not <hi>ſuffer</hi> with Gods people, is it reaſon they ſhould <hi>raigne,</hi> or <hi>rejoice</hi> with them? Such men may juſtly feare, that they ſhall bee blaſted by death, or otherwiſe, that they ſhall never ſee the Good of Gods choſen, or not have any comfort in it, though they ſee it. As the Prophet ſayd to that unbeleeving <hi>Prince,</hi> that doubted the plenty propheſied, as a thing impoſſible, though God ſhould open the windowes of heaven; <hi>Behold (ſayes he) thou ſhalt ſee it with thine eies, but thou ſhalt not eate therof:</hi> 2. <hi>Ki.</hi> 7.2. And it was made good upon him, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. <hi>For the people trode upon him in the gate and he died.</hi> Let that be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is very dangerous to have <hi>private</hi> Spirits,<note place="margin">4. A private Spirit is very danger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us. In reſpect</note> in the <hi>publick</hi> cauſes of God, and his people, both, in reſpect of men, and God: <hi>Newters</hi> commonly fare worſt. Firſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of men,<note place="margin">1. Of men.</note> they at leaſt fall fowle upon ſuch, both ſides ſometimes. Experience tells us of ſome, that for their <hi>Neutralitie</hi> have been plundered by both ſides. See but an inſtance of this in Scripture, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8.15.16.17. How ſharply did <hi>Gideon</hi> revenge himſelfe upon the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> and <hi>Penuel:</hi> for what? for <hi>complying</hi> with his enemies? no, but for their <hi>Neutralitie,</hi> and not affoording him a ſmall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. <hi>He tooke the Princes of Succoth, and the Elders thereof, even threeſcore and ſeventeene men, and thornes of the wilderneſſe, and bryers, and with them he taught the men of Succoth: And he beat downe the towre of Penuel, and ſlew the men of the City.</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:111342:22"/> And I have heard a French ſtorie, of a certaine Prince that in a warre betweene the <hi>Emperour,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King, complyed ſecretly with both ſides, which being diſcovered to both, by letters intercepted, they both agreed to fall upon and breake him, before they fell upon one another.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, if they eſcape with men, God<note place="margin">2. Of God.</note> will be ſure to meete with them worſe. That bitter execration of <hi>Meroz,</hi> is well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nough knowne, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz, ſaies the Angel of the Lord, curſe ye bitterly the inhabitants thereof, becauſe they came not up to helpe the Lord, to helpe the Lord againſt the mightie.</hi> And <hi>Mordecais</hi> meſſage is alſo well knowne: <hi>If thou altogether hold thy peace at this time, delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhall come, but thou and thy Fathers houſe ſhall periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. This is very profitable<note place="margin">5. This is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable.</note> for a mans ſelfe; For what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any man ventures in the publick cauſes of God and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, &amp;c. this is the beſt way, 1. to <hi>Secure</hi> it, 2. to <hi>Repaire</hi> it, 3. to <hi>Improve</hi> it. Firſt, to <hi>ſecure</hi> it,<note place="margin">1. To Secure.</note> be it credit, eſtate, life, any thing: we have a promiſe for this, <hi>He that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it, but he that will loſe his life for my ſake and the Goſpels, ſhall ſave it.</hi> Say the ſame of eſtate, of credit, &amp;c. The way to ſave it, is to loſe it, and the way to loſe it, is to ſave it. Men think, now in theſe troubleſome times, to ſave their own ſtake, by ſparing from the publick cauſe: if things fall out ill, they will have ſomething to live on. No, this is the way to loſe all, in the loſſe of the publick. For in reaſon we ſee, the ſafety of every mans <hi>cabin</hi> in a ſhip, conſiſts in the ſafety of the ſhip, not the ſafety of the ſhip in the ſafety of the cabine; if the ſhip ſinke, what will become of his cabine? Secondly, Suppoſe a man ſhould loſe what he ventures for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Good, yet God can eaſily <hi>repaire</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. To Repare.</note> it. Be it eſtate, or credit, or life it ſelfe: Our Saviour in the former ſpeech ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes a man may loſe his life, for his ſake and the Goſpels; how then can he ſave it? He meanes he ſhall not finally loſe it, but have it againe <hi>repaired</hi> and reſtored. Sometimes a man does but <hi>reſolve</hi> to venture it, or loſe it, and God will not let him loſe it, but ſaves it for him. As when <hi>Abraham</hi> had brought of his heart to offer up his ſonne, God would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111342:23"/> not let him: So here many times, when a man is reſolved to venture all he hath, God is pleaſed to accept of the will for the deed, and to continue it to him; and this is a kind of <hi>Reparation:</hi> But if he doe actually loſe any thing. God is able to make it good to him againe, which men cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies doe, eſpecially not in matter of life. Thirdly, this is very good policie to <hi>improve</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. To Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove.</note> our eſtates, &amp;c. &amp; the readieſt way to advance them: We have a promiſe alſo for this, if we durſt beleeve it; <hi>He that ſhall forſake heuſe, or land, or life, &amp;c. ſhall receive an hundred fold in this life, and in the world to come, life everlaſting.</hi> Men trade for a great deale leſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; eight or ten, or twenty in the hundred, is thought good gaine: but here is a hundred for one; who would not, who ſhould not venture here, if he did beleeve this promiſe to be true?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">6. It is moſt Comfortable. Dulce &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum eſt pro patria mori.</note>6. Laſtly, as it is very <hi>Honourable,</hi> as we ſay, in thoſe Inſtances before mentioned, of <hi>Moſes, David, Jehojada, Mordecai, Nehemiah, Paul,</hi> who ſtand <hi>Renowned</hi> upon Record; ſo it is moſt <hi>Comfortable,</hi> in life, in death, when a man can looke back upon that practick Good which he hath done, and hence collect an evidence of his true <hi>Grace</hi> and reall <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> he may ſay with that holy Apoſtle; <hi>This is our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, even the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in all godly ſincerity we have had our converſation in the world.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. And as this is the comfort of his life; ſo when a man ſhall come to lye upon his ſick bed, or death bed, he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably plead it with God, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (one of the great Reformers of Religion) did in a like caſe, <hi>Lord remember how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight, Jſai.</hi> 38.3. Or as <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> after all his great undertakings for the <hi>publicke Good, Thinke upon mee, my God, for good, according to all that I have done for this people: Nehe.</hi> 5.19. <hi>and</hi> 13.22.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Directed.</note>More might be added, but theſe may ſuffice, in way of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive:</hi> I ſhall only adde a few <hi>directions,</hi> as <hi>meanes</hi> to procure a <hi>publick Spirit,</hi> and then conclude. Take theſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The prime and principall is, to be <hi>Good men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Be Good m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> Religious,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111342:23"/> not only in <hi>ſhew,</hi> but in <hi>truth.</hi> Get from God a new heart and a new ſpirit; the old is a narrow, private, ſelfiſh ſpirit: They that are men of publick ſpirits, muſt be <hi>ſpiritually wiſe men</hi> (as the text cals them:) The wiſdome of the world is to be wiſe to a mans ſelfe, <hi>Nemo ſapit, qui ſibi non ſapit,</hi> is a <hi>proverb</hi> of Nature, he is not wiſe, that is not wiſe to himſelfe: But on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>the wiſdome which is from above, is firſt pure, then gentle, &amp;c. full of mercy and good fruits,</hi> as it is deſcribed, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Wiſe men turne away wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The next is to be <hi>meek</hi> and humble men:<note place="margin">2. Be me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke men.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſe men</hi> in the text are oppoſed to <hi>Scornfull men,</hi> who are ever <hi>proud</hi> men; and we heare of the <hi>meekneſſe of wiſdome, Jam.</hi> 3.13. as we noted at the beginning. Now <hi>Meekneſſe</hi> fits a man for doing of publicke Good, and that two wayes: Firſt, it hath a winning and inſinuating Nature, to allay wrath and fury, and conſequently tumults, contentions, ſeditions, and the like, which bring a City into a <hi>ſnare,</hi> or ſet it on <hi>fire,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is in the Text. For this, <hi>Salomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.1. <hi>A ſoft anſwer turneth away wrath, but grievous words</hi> (of proud and ſcornfull men) <hi>ſtir up anger.</hi> And <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.15. <hi>By long forbearing is a Prince perſwaded, and a ſoft tongue brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the bone.</hi> We have an Inſtance in <hi>Gideon, Judg.</hi> 8.2, 3. and in the <hi>Town-clarke</hi> of <hi>Epheſus, Act.</hi> 19.35. in laying that ſtorme and tumult raiſed by <hi>Demetrius.</hi> Secondly, <hi>meekneſſe</hi> makes a man ſtoop and condiſcend from his owne Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to the meaneſt ſervice and imployment for the <hi>publick Good.</hi> A proud heart as it ever <hi>envyes</hi> thoſe that are <hi>honoured</hi> for their publick ſervice, ſo he <hi>ſcorns</hi> to work for the publick Good, unleſſe in ſome high and honourable way: ſhall ſuch a man as I, ſo parted, ſo gifted, ſo advanced, ſo enriched, ſtoop to ſuch and ſuch meane and low imployments? ſhall I, that am a learned Rabbi of the times, condiſcend to teach the ignorant, ſimple, poore people? leave that to the poore <hi>Curate.</hi> Shall I that am by birth a merit, ennobled, ſhall I leave my fatneſſe, my ſweetneſſe to go up and down for other trees? Now a <hi>meek ſpirit,</hi> will be content to be any thing,<note place="margin">Judg. 9.9.</note> to do any thing, ſo he may but advance the common Good.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:111342:24"/>3. Another direction is, to learne well the firſt Leſſon in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Schoole, <hi>Selfe-deniall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Learn ſelf-deniall.</note> This <hi>Self</hi> is it that hinders all <hi>publick Good.</hi> Men are naturally <hi>lovers of themſelves,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but in theſe laſt and worſt times more then before, as it is propheſied 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Lovers of their owne ſelves,</hi> as it is well rendered by our <hi>Tranſlators,</hi> that is, ſo lovers of themſelves, that they ſcarce love any body elſe, not their owne fleſh and bloud, their poſterity (which yet in ſome caſes they love too well:) As the parents of the blinde man, when there was hazard to acknowledge Chriſt, fairly gave him leave to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for himſelfe, <hi>He is of age, aske him, he ſhall ſpeake for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Theſe words ſpake his parents, becauſe they feared the Jewes; for the Jewes had agreed already, that if any man did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that he was Chriſt, he ſhould be put out of the Synagogue, John</hi> 9.21, 22, 23. <hi>Therefore ſaid his parents, he is of age, aske him.</hi> Never was there more of this <hi>Selfe-love</hi> ſeen, then in theſe times; when we ſee, not only brothers unnaturally to fight againſt brothers, but even children a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt parents, and which is moſt of all unnaturall, even pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents againſt children: The Apoſtle joynes thoſe two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Lovers of themſelves without naturall affection,</hi> in the place afore mentioned. Till this <hi>Selfe,</hi> this <hi>Selfe-love</hi> be denyed, men cannot goe, or looke beyond themſelves.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, to adde no more, get your hearts filled with the <hi>love</hi> of God, and of his people:<note place="margin">4. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve God and his people</note> Love is liberall and bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is kinde; charity envyeth not; charity vaunteth not it ſelfe, is not puft up, doth not behave it ſelfe unſeemly, ſeeketh not her owne</hi> (marke that) <hi>is not eaſily provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, endureth all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4, 5, 6. Yea <hi>Love</hi> will make a man not to thinke his life deare for the publicke Good: <hi>Greater love than this hath no man, than to lay downe his life for his friend, John</hi> 15.13. And therefore the Apoſtle having ſaid, <hi>If God ſo loved us, we ought alſo to love one another,</hi> 1 <hi>John.</hi> 4.11. he ſhewes how far this love will carry us, cap. 3.16. <hi>Hereby perceive we the love of God, becauſe he laid downe his life for us, and we ought to lay downe our lives for the brethren.</hi> We are
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111342:24"/> now at the higheſt degree of <hi>Love,</hi> and the greateſt act of a <hi>publicke ſpirit,</hi> to venture his <hi>life</hi> for the publick Good; Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter love then this hath no man, no man can ſhew greater Goodneſſe then this: Here therefore I ſtay. Conſider what I have ſaid, and the Lord give you underſtanding and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in all things. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order">
            <head>Vltimo Ianuar. <hi>1643.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament; That Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Yelverton,</hi> ſhall from this Houſe give thanks unto Mr. <hi>Daniel Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drey</hi> for the great paines he tooke in the Sermon he this day preached (at the intreaty of this Houſe) at St. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets</hi> in the City of Weſtminſter, it being the day of publicke Humiliation, and to deſire him to Print his Sermon. It is alſo Ordered, that no body ſhall Print his ſaid Sermon, but he whom ſhall be authoriſed by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cawdrey,</hi> under his hand writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <p>I Doe appoint <hi>Charles Greene</hi> and <hi>P. W.</hi> to Print my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DANIEL CAVVDREY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
